<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Duties of communicants, or a treatise, teaching such as purpose to receiue the sacrament of the Lords Supper how they may rightly carrie themselues, before, in, and after the action of receiuing. By R: Preston, preacher of Gods Word at Rushden in Northampton-shire.</title>
            <author>Preston, Richard, d. ca. 1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 159 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 93 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10037</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20284</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100877</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836704</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836704</idno>
            <idno type="VID">990</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10037)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 990)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1183:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Duties of communicants, or a treatise, teaching such as purpose to receiue the sacrament of the Lords Supper how they may rightly carrie themselues, before, in, and after the action of receiuing. By R: Preston, preacher of Gods Word at Rushden in Northampton-shire.</title>
                  <author>Preston, Richard, d. ca. 1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 175, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I.D[awson] for Iohn Ballamie, and are to be sould at the south entrance of the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; page 16 stained; some pages tightly bound, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Sion College. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:990:1"/>
            <p>THE DVTIES OF COMMVNICANTS, <hi>OR</hi> A TREATISE, <hi>Teaching ſuch as purpoſe</hi> to receiue the Sacrament of <hi>the Lords Supper, how they may</hi> rightly carrie themſelues, <hi>before, in, and after the</hi> action of Receiuing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> R: PRESTON, Preacher of Gods Word at <hi>Ruſhden</hi> in Northamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton-ſhire.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 COR. 11.28.</hi>
               </bibl> Let a man examine himſelfe, and ſo let him eate of that Bread, and drinke of that Cup.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>I.D.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Bellamie,</hi> and are to be ſould at the South entrance of the <hi>Royall Exchange.</hi> 1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:990:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:990:2"/>
            <head>TO MY VVELL <hi>AFFECTED FRIEND</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>R: NEWMAN</hi> of <hi>Rotherhith,</hi> neare to <hi>London,</hi> grace, and peace be multiplied.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian friend, I am bold to ſend this ſmall trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe into the World, vnder your protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, moued thereunto, <hi>1.</hi> in reſpect of your zeale to good things, right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:990:3"/>ordered, <hi>1.</hi> by the light of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: <hi>2.</hi> by a wiſe diſcretion; and <hi>3.</hi> by ſincere affection, which hath prouoked you to hate not onely the workes of wicked men, but alſo the vaine doctrines of ſuch Teachers as are not acquainted with the truth. <hi>2.</hi> In reſpect of your practiſe of good things, wherein you goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore many, as an example of good workes. <hi>3.</hi> In reſpect of your affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and kindneſſe to me, who am but a ſtranger vnto you, and farre ſeparated from you. That acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance I haue with you is of no long ſtanding: yet for the time thereof I haue found ſo much fauour, and ſo vnexpected reſpects at your hands that the Law of equitie calleth on me for ſome anſwerable requitall of them. This paper gift therefore I commend vnto your religious care, and Chriſtian practiſe, and
<pb facs="tcp:990:3"/>entreat your friendly acceptance of it, as an inſinuation of my deſire to be thankefull. The matter which it bringeth, is, <hi>A leſſon for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants,</hi> teaching them ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall duties, of good behauiour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in, and after the action of receiuing the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, very neceſſary to be taught, and learned in theſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and formall dayes, ſeeing there be many Communicants, and but few <hi>Catechumeni</hi> Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants, that are worthie partakers of the Sacrament. The ſtile and manner wherin it commeth abroad is plaine, familiar, and fitted for the capacitie, and vnderſtanding of the ſimple, ſo as they that are in the loweſt forme may gather ſomthing from it. In a word, whatſoeuer it is, I haue aduentured the publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, for the vſe, and benefit of
<pb facs="tcp:990:4"/>the Church of God. If either to your ſelfe, or to any member there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it bring any little encreaſe of ſound knowledge, and ſweete fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the myſterie of <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.4.</note> I haue my reward, and that which I can deſire. And ſo beſeeching God to endue you, and yours, with all ſauing grace, to keepe you from falling, and to preſent you fault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, before the preſence of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, with exceeding ioy, through Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; I heartily, and humbly take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Ruſhden.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Nouember 27. 1620.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Yours in all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian affection, R: PRESTON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:990:4"/>
            <head>DVTIES <hi>OF</hi> Communicants.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His age, and time (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we liue) as it is the more ſinnefull, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſantly deuiſe new proiects, and forecaſt to grow ſtronger in all vngodlineſſe: ſo much the more needfull is it, that the duties of holineſſe, and of the true feare of God ſhould
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:990:5"/>be preſſed vpon the conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of people, that the ſtreames of ſinne, and the running iſſue thereof may be ſtaunched, and ſtopt. It becomes vs not to <hi>faſhion our ſelues</hi> (as the Apoſtle demonſtrateth,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.2.</note>) to the ſtampe and Image of the <hi>World,</hi> nor to grow the more ſinfull, as this changeable age giues occaſion, but we ſhould labour to thinke on,<note place="margin">Phil 4.8.</note> and <hi>doe whatſoeuer things are honeſt, iuſt, true, and of a good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut 5.32.33.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And to walke <hi>in all the wayes which the Lord our God hath commanded vs.</hi> It is truely obſerued touching our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, that he <hi>fulfilled all Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 3.15</note> ſo let all our endeuours driue at this, that God (not the world, nor the children therof) may obſerue, and ſay of vs, <hi>Well done good,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 24.45.46. and 25.21.</note> 
               <hi>and profitable ſeruants,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:990:5"/>enter into ioy eternall;</hi> for <hi>you haue had reſpect to al my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements to keep them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and indeed though there be ſmall power, or no abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie at all in vs to fulfil as was in Chriſt, yet there is no man, but is bound. 1. To all duties of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; godly life. 2. To all duties concerning outward righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which men claime. 3. To all particular duties charged vpon him by vertue of that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie, whereof he is a member, whether Church, Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, or familie. For this <hi>is the will of God,</hi> that we ſhuld pro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt, and ſet forward our ſelues to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery <hi>good worke,</hi> that we ſhould ſtriue vnto perfection, &amp; ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and <hi>beare the image of Chriſt in vs againe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.1.</note> Oh that there were ſuch an heart <hi>in euery one of vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theſ. 4.3.</note> that <hi>we might feare God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 5.29.</note> 
               <hi>and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:990:6"/>keepe his Commandements, then would it goe well with vs, and our children after vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as generally we ſtand in need of all incitements, and prouocations to doe all the things that God hath enioined vs by vertue of our Callings, Generall, or Particuler: ſo more particularly ought the duties of the Sacrament of the Lords Supper to be vrged, and preſſed vpon vs. 1. Becauſe we are dull and vnapt to conceiue, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the myſteries thereof, much like to blunt iron that needs much ſharpening. 2. We are readie to forget, our memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries like Siues, or Riuen diſhes drop out good leſſons, as faſt as they are powred in. 3. We de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue our ſelues in the receipt of daintie Cookt meates at the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:990:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lords Table, taking that for ordinarie, which is ſacred bread. 4. We ſuppoſe no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of ſuch meate (ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing holy things) when our own Tables, often in a day are fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with choice diſhes. 5 We are ignorant of the end, and vſe of ſuch a bleſſed ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet: and laſtly, hauing taſted thereof we remaine vnthanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, or elſe ſtrangely conceited of a Non proficiencie by feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> All which impediments the Lord nearly eſpying in vs, hath prouided his Miniſters, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be 1. Stewards: whom he hath bound not onely to prouide things neceſſarie to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable partaking of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but alſo to acquaint vs carefully vpon what conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:990:7"/>we may receiue the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 1. Doctrine appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the right vſe of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament muſt not be kept ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret. 2. The danger of vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie receiuing muſt be fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewed. 3. The precious muſt be ſeparated from the vile:<note place="margin">Ier. 15.19.</note> 
               <hi>holy things may not be giuen to dogs:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7.6.</note> And 4. together with perſonall ſanctification,<note place="margin">2. Chron. 35.6.</note> muſt be a <hi>prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> God hath made his Miniſters his <hi>Remembrancers,</hi> not onely for putting him in mind of his couenant towards his people, but alſo in that they muſt bee reſtleſſe in whetting Chriſtian duties vpon the people, among which, the duties concerning the Sacrament may be recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; For, firſt, there is none ſo farre inſtructed in the myſteries
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:990:7"/>thereof, but is wanting in much knowledge, and to ſeeke in his practiſe, and therefore had need of ſtirring vp.<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>I will not be negligent</hi> (ſayth S. <hi>Peter,</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to thoſe that had know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and were eſtabliſhed in the preſent truth,) to <hi>put you in remembrance of theſe things.</hi> And ſecondly, no man is ſo ſtrong, and ſo ſound of memorie, but he ſtands in neede of a daily confirmation, and often reno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
            <p>Now as God is thus carefull for vs, that we might not be left deſtitute of nouriſhment for our ſoules, nor forgetfull of his mercies in the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> but ſends vs his Miniſters to be <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,</hi> and <hi>Remembrancers,</hi> to put vs in minde of our Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant made with him, to teach
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:990:8"/>vs what things are neceſſarie to the right vſing of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to charge vs as from his immediate perſon, not to dare to <hi>prouoke him to anger,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.22.</note> by an irreuerent, and prophane dealing with thoſe things, that are of ſo holy a nature as the Sacraments. Then muſt we la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to poſſeſſe our memories, and to haue our hearts prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for a remembrance, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of ſuch leſſons as are taught, and deliuered con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>Firſt, leaſt wee ſinne againſt Chriſt, by a ſecond daily cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of him by our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, leaſt we heape dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation vpon our bodies, and ſoules.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, leaſt we be ſharply reprehended of the Lord for
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:990:8"/>our forgetfulneſſe, and neglect of ſuch an heauenly banquet, as is his laſt Supper.</p>
            <p>Conſidering therefore the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of worthie receiuing, and the danger of thoſe that ruſh vpon the Lords Supper, without ſerious preparation, my purpoſe is to ſhew how we may become worthy receiuers, and ſo may preuent all Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments threatned. If we would be approued as worthie, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers in the Lords ſight, then a three-fold religious beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour is required at all our hands.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Before we receiue.</item>
               <item>2. In the action of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing.</item>
               <item>3. After our receiuing.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, our behauiour before we receiue conſiſteth in foure duties principally.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:990:9"/>
               <item>1. In a purpoſe, and reſolution to receiue ſo often, as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of receiuing is offered.</item>
               <item>2. In a preparation to receiue.</item>
               <item>3. In knowledge of that we do receiue.</item>
               <item>4. In a longing deſire, and hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring appetite after that we receiue.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt dutie before we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue is, that we purpoſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue, and ſet downe with our ſelues to receiue, and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate at the Lords Table with the reſt of his people, ſo often as God in his wiſe prouidence of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth the occaſion. So that as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid of the whole Law of God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> 
               <hi>I haue purpoſe, and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to keepe thy Law;</hi> ſo muſt we all of vs in this particular, purpoſe to receiue when God
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:990:9"/>offereth the opportunitie.</p>
            <p>The reaſon is becauſe in this Sacrament God of his infinite goodneſſe,<note place="margin">Reaſon.</note> and mercie offers vnto vs his onely ſonne Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>the true bread of life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh: 6.48.</note> 
               <hi>to ſeede our ſoules to eternall life;</hi> and Chriſt alſo offers himſelfe, <hi>I am the liuing bread which come downe from heauen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">33.35.51.</note> 
               <hi>if any man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate of this bread, he ſhall liue for euer, and the bread that I will giue him is my fleſh, &amp;c.</hi> Now if God offer his ſonne, and his ſonne be willing to come vnto vs to be our bread of life, both vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hankefull vnto God, &amp; Chriſt, and vnmindfull of our owne good ſhall we be, if we purpoſe not to receiue, but refuſe ſuch a great mercie of the Lord, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t is fitly offered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> We purpoſe to receiue<note place="margin">Ob.</note>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:990:10"/>this Sacrament, though not ſo often as perhaps you would haue vs, we will receiue it once a yeare, at Eaſter time, and that is ſufficient, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> To this I anſwere,<note place="margin">Sol.</note> that it is not ſufficient to receiue it once a yeare, at Eaſter, and no more: but it ought to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at all other times, euen ſo often as God in his prouidence ſhall call vs vnto it. Theſe are my Reaſons for it.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> 1. The firſt reaſon is taken from the Commandement, God hath commanded it: and Chriſt alſo hath inſtituted it: The Lord ſaid vnto his people of Iſrael, that the feaſt of the Paſſeouer, (in ſtead whereof we haue the Lords Supper) ſhould be kept as a memoriall, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>holy feaſt</hi> vnto him,<note place="margin">Exod. 12.14</note> not by fits<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:990:10"/>and ſtarts, when they would, but as hee had commanded them <hi>throughout their generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as an ordinance for euer;</hi> And Chriſt himſelfe in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, inſtituting this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſayth vnto his Diſciples, and in them to euery one of vs, that looke for the ſame ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Take, eate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.26</note> without any limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of time, giuing vs to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that ſo often as hee commandeth to take, ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten we in obedience ſhould bee readie to receiue: and beſides, this is a part of Gods worſhip, ſet downe in the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and ought to be obeyed.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> 2. To receiue often, is, and euer hath beene the practiſe of all faithfull men from time to time, both vnder the Olde and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:990:11"/>New Teſtament: Hence it is, that we read in the Olde Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the man that would not celebrate the Paſſeouer, with the reſt of Gods people, ſhould bee excommunicated, and <hi>cut off from the great Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 9.13</note> And ſo common was this practiſe of the faithfull in the Primitiue Church, as that it was made a Sabbaoth dayes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, ſo that we ſee in the Acts of the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Act. 2.46.</note> 
               <hi>Hearing of the Word,</hi> and breaking of bread goe together:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.26.</note> and <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth, <hi>ſo often as ſee eate this bread,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Alij quotidie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municant corpori, &amp; ſanguini Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minico.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Noting thereby the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Sacrament: And indeed we finde, that in former times, ſome did partake and communicate euery day; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers certaine ſolemne, and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiuall daies, others vpon Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:990:11"/>and the Lords day, others vpon the Lords day onely:<note place="margin">Alij certis diebus acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piunt, alibi nullus dies intermittitur quo non offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur: Alibi ſabbato tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp; Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minico: Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minico. Aug. Epiſ. <hi>118.</hi> ad Ianuarcum. Legimus om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Eccleſiae Congregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne celebrata fuiſſe hac myſteria. Chry. ſuper Mat. Homil. <hi>16.</hi> Dies Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicus, dies panis, dies lucis, &amp;c.</note> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſo often as the Papiſts do offer their Maſſe. And we read that in euery Congregation, &amp; meeting of people together in the houſe of God, the myſteries of the Lords Supper were cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated. And hence it is, that the Sabbaoth hath three names giuen vnto it. Firſt, the Lords day. Secondly, the day of eating bread: and thirdly, the day of light.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> 3. If a man neglect this feaſt, and banquet, when God offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it, and calleth him vnto it, he knoweth not whether euer he will make him partaker of it afterwards in mercie, or no: when his feaſt was prepared, and his Table furniſhed, the gueſts that refuſed to come (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:990:12"/>bidden) <hi>were not worthie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 22.8.9.</note> neither could they be admitted <hi>to taſte of his ſupper:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 14.24</note> but other gueſts that were in the <hi>hie wayes and vnder hedges were compelled to come in,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> 
               <hi>that the houſe might be filled, and the wedding furniſhed.</hi> Oh that in this our <hi>day,</hi> men would thinke vpon the Lords kinde Inuitation of vs to his <hi>well ſtored Table.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 55.1.2.</note>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 9.5.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>4</label> 4. Vnleſſe a man doth often receiue, he cutteth himſelfe off from Chriſt the head, and from the body, which is the church: for this Sacrament is a ſigne of that vnion, and communion which we haue with Chriſt our head, and of that fellowſhip, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and communion, which one member of the Church hath with another, and how they are ſeparated from all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:990:12"/>heretiques, &amp; prophane perſons of the world. Chriſt ſayth to <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 13.8.</note> 
               <hi>vnleſſe thou ſuffer me to waſh thy feete, thou haſt no part in me:</hi> So vnleſſe in this Sacrament we ſuffer Chriſt to waſh vs with his bloud, we haue no part in him: And againe ſayth our Sauiour,<note place="margin">Ioh: 15.6.</note> 
               <hi>If a man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide not in me, he is caſt forth as a branch that is withered, and men gather them, and caſt them into the fire, and they are burned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>5</label> 5. He that neglecteth this Sacrament when it is offered, neglecteth the food of his own ſoule, and a ſpeciall ſeale, and pledge of his faith, &amp; of Gods loue towards him in Chriſt: for Chriſt the true bread of life is offered in this Sacrament, and ſo often as God ſendeth vs to this Sacrament, ſo often he ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:990:13"/>vs to a new token, ſeale, and pledge of his ancient loue: Now none will bee content, I thinke, with feeding the body once a yeare, nay, ſcarce once a day. What leanneſſe, and lacke of grace is this, to be content to haue our ſoules fedd with the bread of life but once a yeare: The oftener our friends ſend vs loue-tokens, and pledges of their affections, the more doe we reioyce, and with thankfull hearts receiue them; but this token that GOD ſends vs is Chriſt, with all his benefits, let vs therefore receiue him with prayſe, and with much ioy, and whenſoeuer, he is offered to the hand of our faith.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>6</label> 6. Laſtly, to receiue Chriſt but once a yeare, and no oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, came firſt in by the Romiſh
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:990:13"/>Church, who turned the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Supper into the Propitiatory ſacrifice of the Maſſe,<note place="margin">Concil. trid: ſeſſ. <hi>13.</hi> Can. <hi>9.</hi> Mornae: c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tra Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam. pa. <hi>229</hi> Willet. Synop. Pag. <hi>629.</hi>
               </note> where they will offer Chriſt, but not receiue him: wheras ſtill to this day all other Churchet among the Grecians Armenians, Syrians, Muſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites, Germanes, &amp;c. retaine an often Communion in one yeare.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> The vſe of this point ſerueth to confute;</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Papiſts that goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to diſanuall the neceſſarie vſe, and often receiuing of the Lords Supper, binding lay men to a ſet time, and ſeaſon of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing, to Eaſter time onely, whereas Chriſt requireth an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten repetition of his death, and a diligent comming vnto his Supper.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:990:14"/>2. The Atheiſts that make no reckoning of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, perhaps they will come once in a month to the Church to ſaue a forfeit, but ſcarce once in a yeare to receiue the Lords Supper, and when they receiue it, they make no more account of it then ſome three halpenie Ordinarie: there is ſuch ſcant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Grace among them, that they feele no ſweetneſſe in it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Temporizing Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicants that communicate at ſome ſeaſon of the yeare, or at ſome ſuppoſed good times, onely as though ſeaſons, and Moones, and the influences of the skie, gaue vertue to Gods ordinances.</p>
            <p n="4">4. All wicked people, that abſtaine from this Supper, for
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:990:14"/>very negligence, in want of preparation, or becauſe they are fallen out with their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and cannot be in perfect charitie. To theſe and all ſuch it may be ſaid, that they are grieuous ſinners, and great tranſgreſſors of Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements; they are open contemners of the practiſe of the faithfull, they incurre the wrath and diſpleaſure of the Maſter of this feaſt, ſo as in Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and true Iudgement, he may tell them, they ſhall neuer taſt of his meate any more, they cut themſelues off from Chriſt, and from vnitie, and concord with his Church; they deſpiſe the foode of their ſoules, and the pledges, and tokens of Gods loue, and they vtterly caſt off the ſeales of their owne ſaluation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:990:15"/>
               <hi>Ob:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ob.</note> Yea, but S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth, <hi>that it is better for a man to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine then come for the worſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.34.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sol.</note> It is true indeed, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all ſuch as come vpon a good intent, and yet without knowledge of that they come for, or ſuch as come for cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, or companie, without examination of themſelues, or ſuch as (becauſe they would be counted Chriſtians) <hi>come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their wedding garment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 22.12.</note> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing neither faith, nor a good conſcience, doe ſinne greatly in comming, as well as the former in not comming at all: but yet theſe can be no preiudice, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſcouragement to them tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are rightly prepared. Other mens ſinnes muſt not be block<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in their way to this banquet, to hinder them from it.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:990:15"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> 2. This ſerues for our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. If ſo often as the bloud of Chriſt is ſhed, it is ſhed for the remiſſion of ſinnes, then we ought often to receiue it, that our ſins accordingly may be forgiuen.<note place="margin">Ambroſ. de Sacra: lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap: <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> Make haſt to come oftentimes vnto this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for when this thing is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>igently, and continually done,<note place="margin">Ignatius in Epiſt: ad Epheſ:</note> the powers of Sathan are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled, which turneth his actes into <hi>firie darts,</hi> to moue men to ſinne. And albeit thou make a ſtand at thy ſinnes, yet if they be not ſo great, as for them thou ought to be excommunicate, thou mayeſt not ſeparate thy ſelfe from the medicine of the bodie and bloud of Chriſt: for,<note place="margin">Hilarius de Conſecra: diſt: <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> it is to be feared, leaſt that hee, which withdraweth himſelfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ong from the bodie of Chriſt,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:990:16"/>be vtterly eſtranged from ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. He therefore that ceaſed to ſinne, let him not ceaſe to communicate.</p>
            <p>Oh therefore examine,<note place="margin">Theophilact in <hi>1.</hi> Cor. cap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> and bolt out thy conſcience, and ſo come vnto theſe heauenly my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, not on the feſtiuall, not on the vnfeſtiuall dayes onely, but at all times when thou fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thy ſelfe readie, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond dutie in our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour before wee receiue, is Preparation, whereby we muſt prepare, and fit our ſelues to a right receiuing of this holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, this is verie neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: the People of God are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to prepare themſelues before-hand,<note place="margin">Pſal. 57.7. 2. Chro 30.12.13.</note> to all the parts of Gods worſhip, and ſeruice, and therefore much more to this
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:990:16"/>holy Sacrament. This Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is called Examination: <hi>Let a man</hi> (ſayth the Apoſtle) <hi>examine himſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.28.</note> 
               <hi>and ſo let him eate of this bread, and drinke of this cup.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This examination is three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde;</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Of our ſinnes paſt and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</item>
               <item>2. Of our reconciliation with God.</item>
               <item>3. Of our reconciliation with our brethren.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, for the Examination of our ſelues, touching our ſinnes, paſt or preſent, that is ſet down in the Lamentations of <hi>Ieremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 3.40.41.</note> where the Prophet ſayth, <hi>Come, let vs ſearch, trie, and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine our owne wayes, and ſo turne againe to the Lord:</hi> but howe muſt we examine our ſelues,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:990:17"/>ſurely by the Law of God, we muſt know that, and take that into our hands,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.13</note> as a glaſſe to behold our ſelues in, for it will ſhew vs all our ſinnes,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.10.</note> originall, actuall, &amp;c. Yea, not onely our ſinnes, but the puniſhment of ſinnes: the Law as a lyne will ſhew vs all our crookedneſſe, and fetch vs in by ſuch circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, as wherby, we ſhall not content our ſelues with a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion in groſſe, that <hi>we are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> bvt we ſhall confeſſe our ſinnes to be out of meaſure ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: and like the Kings Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, ſift, and exaggerate euery circumſtance of our ſinne, to make it as foule as can be, that our harts may be beaten downe in the ſence of our miſerie: and that we may cry out of our ſelues: <hi>Alas, What haue I done?</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:990:17"/>And in this Examination, wee <hi>muſt iudge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.31.32.</note> 
               <hi>and condemne our ſelues, that ſo we<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> be not iudged, and condemned of the Lord.</hi> We muſt doe, as the Iudge doth in his examining of a theefe, or an euill doer: firſt, ſet our ſelues at the barre of the Lords ſeate, to whom we muſt bee countable: ſecondly, make diligent ſearch into our offences: thirdly, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce witneſſes: fourthly, accuſe our ſelues, and plead guiltie: fiftly, confeſſe the particulars; and ſixtly, paſſe ſentence of death vpon our ſelues, iudging <hi>our ſelues a people worthie to bee cut off.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond thing whereof we muſt examine our ſelues, is whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our ſinnes be pardoned, whether the ſeale of Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is ſet to the pardon, whether
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:990:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:990:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:990:19"/>Chriſt hath acquitted, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged <hi>vs for our offences,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.13 14.</note> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we bee reconciled vnto God, or in the ſtate of grace, or no: this Sacrament profits none but ſuch as are in Chriſt: <hi>Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine your ſelues</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>whether you be in the faith or no,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 13.5.</note> 
               <hi>proue your ſelues, know you not that Chriſt is in you, except you be Reprobates?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We may know whether wee be reconciled vnto God, and haue gotten pardon of our ſins, two wayes.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. If we feele that we haue truely beleeued.</item>
               <item>2. If we perceiue that wee haue truely repented.</item>
            </list>
            <p>For the firſt wee ſhall know, that wee haue truely beleeued,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> by examining three ſignes of our faith.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:990:19"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, if we finde, wee haue receiued the ſpirit of grace, and the ſauing gifts and graces thereof, which they that true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y beleeue doe receiue, then may we know that wee are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled vnto GOD, and haue true faith: <hi>Hereby</hi> (ſayth Saint IOHN) <hi>Wee know that wee dwell in him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh: 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>and hee in is becauſe hee hath giuen vs of his Spirit</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And among all the gifts of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Spirit, earneſt, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Prayer, is a note of true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aith, for therein the Spirit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f GOD giueth vs confidence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd boldneſſe, to crie,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.15.26.</note> 
               <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a Father, with ſighes, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bbes, that cannot bee expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, we ſhall know we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue faith, if there bee an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:990:20"/>ward battell againſt feare, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt infidelitie, againſt ſinne, and againſt the temptation of Sathan, ſo as through Gods bleſſing we doe ouercome.<note place="margin">Gal. 5.17.</note> 
               <hi>The fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpirit, and the ſpirit againſt the fleſh:</hi> Euery croſſe, puffe of winde of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or temptation, vnſetleth the vnbeleeuer; but the beleeuer <hi>will not feare though the earth bee moued:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 46.2.</note> his faith is like Iron, the more it is beaten, the harder it is; or the waters, the more they are preſſed, the ſtronger they are, and the more impetuous, as we ſee in the Sea betweene two rockes, and in Riuers vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Arches of a bridge.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, the third ſigne of faith, is a ſenſe, and feeling of the fruit of faith: as 1. Of peace of Conſcience: ſecondly, of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:990:20"/>
               <hi>Being iuſtified by faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>we haue peace towards God through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> thirdly, of Ioy, which is called <hi>vnſpeakeable, and glorious:</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> Wee <hi>ioy in God through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, by whom we haue receiued the attonement:</hi> fourthly, of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification,<note place="margin">Act. 15.9.</note> 
               <hi>faith purifieth the heart,</hi> it ſuffereth no vncleane thoughts, vnlawfull luſts, or wandring motions to harbour there, it purgeth <hi>out the old lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi> and by little and little, tranſchangeth it into a newe lumpe: fiftly, of obedience; <hi>We haue receiued grace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtleſhip, that obedience might bee giuen vnto the faith:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.8.</note> And <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham by faith (when he was called) obeyed God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note> ſixtly, of loue, <hi>faith worketh by loue,</hi> both towardes God &amp; man, towards him that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:990:21"/>begate, and him that is begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, yea, and him that is not yet begotten: ſeauenthly, Of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes,<note place="margin">Act. 13.48.</note> 
               <hi>ſo many as were ordained to eternall life, beleeued.</hi> And againe, <hi>All that beleeue in Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 10.43.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall receiue remiſsion of ſinnes, &amp;c.</hi> The inward ſenſe of ſuch fruits as theſe, argueth faith to be in the heart of him, that beareth them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> For our Repentance, we ſhall know that wee haue repented by theſe foure ſignes of it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, if we feele by examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that we haue tender harts, euen like melting waxe,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.10.</note> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually mourning and grieuing for our ſinnes, and offences: <hi>the ſacrifices of God are a contrite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.17. Pſal. 34.18. And 77 3. And 143.4. Iſa. 42.3. Ioel 2.3. Act 2.37.</note> 
               <hi>broken, afflicted, anguiſhed, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed bruſed, rent, and pricked heart.</hi> He that vnfainedly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penteth,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:990:21"/>doth lament, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile his former ſinnes, and conceiueth ſuch inward griefe, that <hi>his heart doth melt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 22.19.</note> 
               <hi>and his ſpirit is ſore troubled within him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 8.15.</note> Our ſinnes ſhould be our grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſorrow, nothing ſhould goe ſo neare our hearts as they: and therefore the Lord ſaith, that when men are brought to a true ſight of their ſinnes, they ſhall mourne for them, <hi>as one that mourneth for his owne ſonne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 12.10.</note> 
               <hi>and be ſorrie as one is ſorrie for his firſt borne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, we ſhall know that we haue repented, if wee feele our ſelues prone, and forward to hate with perfect hatred, and deteſtation, all our ſinnes paſt, or preſent, &amp; our ſelues for our ſinnes, whereby we haue offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded our gracious, and mercifull
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:990:22"/>Father.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.11.</note> This is called <hi>Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or <hi>diſpleaſure,</hi> ſignifying how much euery penitent man is angrie, and diſpleaſed with himſelfe; and thus did <hi>Iob</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of his ſinnes, ſaying,<note place="margin">Iob 42.6.</note> 
               <hi>I ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre my ſelfe in duſt, and aſhes;</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7 24.</note> when he called him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, a <hi>Perſecutor, and a miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wretch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, we ſhall know our repentance to be ſound, if for the time to come we purpoſe, and reſolue to leaue, &amp; forſake all our former ſinnes,<note place="margin">Si vis eſſe verus paeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens, ceſſa a peccato et no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li amplius peccare quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam inais eſt paenite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia, quamſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s coinquamt culpa. Bern. Medita: c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> yea, all manner of iniquitie. It is not ſufficient for vs to be inwardly ſorrowfull, but we muſt put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all our ſinnes: and if thou wilt be a true penitent, ceaſe from ſinne, and ſinne no more, for that repentance is vaine, which after-ſinnes doe defile.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:990:22"/>It was the great commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Niniuites,</hi> that <hi>they turned from their euill wayes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ion: 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>and from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he wickedneſſe that was in their hands.</hi> Neither muſt wee thinke it ſufficient for vs to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake ſome ſinnes, and retaine o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome, or to exchange one ſinne for another, but we muſt endeuour to forſake, and ſel all,<note place="margin">Mat. 13.44.</note> not one curſed <hi>Amalekite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.3.</note> that ſighteth againſt our ſoule, muſt be ſpared, how deare ſo euer it be:<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.11.</note> 
               <hi>Cleanſe your ſelues</hi> (ſayth the Apoſtle) <hi>from all filthineſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.1.</note> 
               <hi>both of the fleſh, and ſpirit. Mortifie all your earthly members;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3.5.8. Pſal. 119.3. Pſal. 101.4.</note> 
               <hi>caſt away all things that are diſpleaſing to God: worke none iniquitie; none at all, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, we ſhall know wee haue repented, if we bring forth fruits worthie the amendment
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:990:23"/>of life, if we ſtudie, and endeour nor to breake the leaſt of Gods Commandements,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.5.6.</note> but <hi>haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect vnto one, and all: If we p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t on the new man which after God is created in righteouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.24.</note> 
               <hi>and true holineſſe:</hi> if we ſeeke to pleaſe God in all things,<note place="margin">Pſal. 139.20.21.</note> 
               <hi>hating that which he hateth, and louing that which he loueth;</hi> and if we exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe our ſelues to haue a <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence voyd of offence towards God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 24.16.</note> 
               <hi>and man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third part of our Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſtands in the tryall, and examination of our ſelues, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we be reconciled to our neighbours and brethren; this is as neceſſarie, as the former<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and a true touch-ſtone, to trie whether we be reconciled vnto God, or no. The holy Ghoſt ſayth in one of the Epiſtles of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:990:23"/>Saint <hi>Iohn: that he is a lyar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ioh: 4.20</note> 
               <hi>who ſayth, he loueth God, and hateth his brother.</hi> The true ground of this Reconciliation is the loue of God the Creatour: All the loue of man muſt iſſue from the loue of God; and all duties of the ſecond Table muſt be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in the firſt; neither ought any creature to be loued ſo farre, as it is an enemie, and hatefull to God the Creator. I hate the wicked, that is, ſo farre as wicked, namely, their practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, not their perſons.</p>
            <p>There are certaine ſignes and tokens wherby our loue, to our brethren; and Reconciliation with our neighbours may bee rightly diſcerned.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is, for a man to feele himſelfe willing and readie to forgiue his neighbour any treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:990:24"/>or offence he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt him, franckly, or freely; yea, though he haue offended him often, euen vnto ſeauentie <hi>times ſeuen times:</hi> He that hath ten thouſand Talents forgiuen him, will not eaſily take his brother by the throat for two-pence. The Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement is to forgiue one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.32</note> euen as <hi>God for Chriſts ſake forgaue vs.</hi> The example is, <hi>Be yee mercifull as your heauenly father is mercifull;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 6.36.</note> he forgiueth all, freely, perfectly; he is firſt in forgiueneſſe, hee forgiueth, and forgetteth too. The forme of our petition of mercie is,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.12.</note> 
               <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue vs, as we forgiue others:</hi> and the conditionall promiſe is, <hi>if ye forgiue men their treſpaſſes your heauenly father will forgiue you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 14.15.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:990:24"/>
               <hi>Ob:</hi> But I am daily prouoked,<note place="margin">Ob.</note> and how ſhall I forgiue?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol:</hi> Many in this caſe ſuffer their patience to be broken,<note place="margin">Sol.</note> not bridling their anger, and iudge meekeneſſe, putting vp, and not reuenging iniuries to be baſeneſſe, cowardiſe, and weakeneſſe. But the word of God tells vs,<note place="margin">Luk. 17.4.</note> that we muſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue our brethren, though they <hi>ſinne ſeuen times a day againſt vs,</hi> that <hi>we muſt not be ouercome of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ro. 12.21.</note> 
               <hi>but ouercome euill with good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi> this is bow, arrow, ſword, piſtoll, &amp; a ſurer conqueſt then many blowes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond note whereby we may diſcerne our Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with our neighbours, is loue vnfained;<note place="margin">Rom. 12.9.</note> 
               <hi>Let loue be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſsimulation:</hi> It muſt not be hypocriticall, from the teeth
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:990:25"/>outward, and fawning; but loue muſt come from a pure heart; <hi>Let vs not loue in word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ioh: 3.18.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; tongue, but in deed, and truth:</hi> Diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling is euill in all things, but it is worſt of all in neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, as the moſt contrarie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> corrupting cauſe of friendſhip. Things moſt excellent,<note place="margin">Corruptio op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timi eſt peſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſima.</note> corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted become the worſe: As there is nothing more excellent, and comfortable to the life of man, then true, and vnfained loue; ſo there is nothing more vile, then when it is counterfeit, and diſſembled.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third marke of Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation with our brethren, &amp; neighbours, is Reſtitution, to be readie and willing to ſatisfie them, and to make amends for any wrong or iniurie done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. We haue a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:990:25"/>example of it in good <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus,</hi> who being conuerted, ſtood forth in the preſence of Chriſt, and made this proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>If I haue taken any thing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 19.8.</note> 
               <hi>from any man by forged cauillation I reſtore to him foure-fold.</hi> This alſo was the Law for theft,<note place="margin">Exod. 22.1.</note> that <hi>if a man ſteale an Oxe, or a ſheepe, and kill it, or ſell it, he ſhall reſtore fiue oxen for the Oxe, and foure ſheepe, for the ſheepe.</hi> And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Dauid</hi> adiudged the man that had taken from his poore neighbour his only ſheepe,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.16.</note> that he ſhould reſtore him foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob:</hi> But what if a neighbour be ſo poore,<note place="margin">Ob:</note> that he is no way able to make Reſtitution, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol:</hi> Then ſurely his pouerty may be diſpenſed withall,<note place="margin">Sol:</note> for as
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:990:26"/>the Prouerbe is, <hi>Where nothing is to be had, the King muſt looſe his right;</hi> And <hi>neceſsitie hath no law.</hi> But yet if a man be neuer ſo poore, he muſt teſtifie his deſire to reſtore if he were able, and no doubt but it will be well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth note is friendly ſpeech, A man that hath <hi>friends muſt ſhew himſelfe friendly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 18.24.</note> no contentious, nor rayling word muſt goe out of his mouth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob:</hi> But my neighbour de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues rather ſharp,<note place="margin">Ob.</note> then friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly words, may I not reproue him?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol:</hi> Yes,<note place="margin">Sol.</note> but it muſt be in a friendly manner, hauing warre with his vices, but peace, with his perſon. Hee breakes not Gods peace, nor the Kinges peace, nor the Churches peace,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:990:26"/>nor the league of true neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood, who hauing a good calling reproues, but he that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyeth not the truth to ſpeake ill of an vndeſeruing neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, argues a deuilliſh minde; to ſpeake well of a good neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, a ciuill minde: to ſpeake well of an euill deſeruing neighbour, a Chriſtian minde.</p>
            <p>In this caſe of friendly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe, follow the direction of our Sauiour CHRIST;<note place="margin">Mat. 18.15 16.17.</note> 
               <hi>If thy brother offend againſt thee,</hi> (that is, in thy ſight, for an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence committed before thee is a ſcandall vnto thee) <hi>goe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue him betweene thee, and him alone: If he ſhall hearken vnto thee, thou haſt wonne thy brother: but if he ſhall not harken vnto thee; take vnto thee two, or three, that by the mouth of two or three wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:990:27"/>euery word may bee eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, &amp;c.</hi> This is the friendl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> courſe which we muſt take wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an offenſiue neighbour. And he chance to be abſent, that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cannot reproue him to his fac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yet wee muſt not publiſh h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhame behinde his backe: <hi>He that vttereth infamie is a fool<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> The ſecret faults of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours we are to conceale,<note place="margin">Pro. 10.18.</note> and couer, if they be committed o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> infirmitie:<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.8.</note> for, <hi>Loue couereth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> multitude of faults.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The fift marke of our recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation with our brethren, is a compaſſionate, and a fellow feeling ioy, or miſerie. A truly reconciled neighbour is a <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 10.33</note> grieuing at the trouble of his brother; he will ſet to his ſhoulders, and lift him vp, yea, euery way he offereth himſelfe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:990:27"/>willing, and readie to helpe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elieue him to the vttermoſt of his power and abilitie. In this reſpect <hi>Paul</hi> gaue great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations of the Macedoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns, <hi>That to their power, yea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 8.1.2.3.</note> 
               <hi>and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eyond their power, they were wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing of themſelues</hi> to relieue one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nother in their pouertie and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aiſerie.</p>
            <p>And according to this rule, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd example the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſtle exhorted the <hi>Romanes to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eioyce with them that reioyce,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.15</note> 
               <hi>and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> weepe with them that weepe:</hi> And the <hi>Phillippians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>Not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oke euery man on his own things, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut euery one alſo on the things of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiection.</hi> But muſt we in all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccaſions be ſo affected as our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eighbours?<note place="margin">Ob.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol:</hi> No:<note place="margin">Sol.</note> the drunkard doth
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:990:28"/>reioyce in his drinking: It <hi>is ſport to a foole to do wickedly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 10.23.</note> and <hi>folly is ioy to him that is deſtitute of vnderſtanding;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 15.21.</note> let them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioice alone, let vs rather weepe.</p>
            <p>Againe, Many will weepe when they are croſſed in their taſts,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 13.2</note> as <hi>Amnon</hi> is ſicke for his ſiſter <hi>Thamar;</hi> and <hi>Ahab</hi> for <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both</hi> his Vincyard:<note place="margin">1. Kin. 21.4</note> Here we are not to weepe with them, but for them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi> Is it ſo that we muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare our ſelues before we come to the Lords Supper, by exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our ſelues: firſt, touching our ſinnes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſecondly, Our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with God thirdly, Our Reconciliation with our brethren: Then in this poynt as in a glaſſe, we may ſee howe many ſorts of people fayle in their preparation, and commit
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:990:28"/>a fearefull ſinne; and profit lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or nothing at all by this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y ordinance of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, all ſuch as remaine in the obduracy, and hardneſſe of their hearts, and neuer enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Examination of themſelues for their ſinnes: Theſe are they who neuer take the glaſſe of Gods law into their hands, to ſee, and behold their owne fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hineſſe. Glaſſes they will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake into their hands to ſee, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ehold their owne beautie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ride, vanitie of apparell, &amp;c. But not to ſee their ignorance, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>runkenneſſe, infidelitie, pride of minde, ſwearing, contempt of God, and his ordinances; fornication, &amp;c. they neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ring themſelues to the Barre of Gods Iudgement, arraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng, accuſing, iudging, and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:990:29"/>condemning themſelues for their ſinnes, but rather like the proud <hi>Phariſie</hi> they iuſtifie, and excuſe themſelues; they are no ſuch great offenders as men take them for, they hope they are prepared, &amp;c. Well the Lord ſayth to all theſe:<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note> 
               <hi>What doe you with mine ordinances, and hate to be reformed, caſting my Lawes behinde your backes.</hi> I will wound your hairie pate, and the ſcalpe of all thoſe that ſleepe in ſinne, and ſo God in the ſeueritie of Iuſtice ſharpens his wrath againſt them, that the edge of it might bee keene in the day of wrath. Therefore let all ſuch neuer dare to come to this Table in their pollutions: Will a man entertaine a filthie Leprous gueſt, or ſhall he haue a kinde welcome to his Table,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:990:29"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat comes in a beſmeared, and dirtie apparell? No ſurely. No more will God ſuffer polluted, and filthy perſons to eate of his Table, and though they come and ſit downe (as many ſinfull men doe,) yet they are not wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come gueſts, and as the ſaying is, He had rather haue their roome, then their companie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, there are another ſort, that faile in their Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, namely, ſuch as are more ciuill, and peraduenture breake not out into ſuch outrage of ſinning, as the former doth; yet are ſecure, and labour not to know whether they be in the ſtate of grace, or reconciled vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, or no, they examine not their faith, and Repentance by the ſignes of faith, and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; they can be content
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:990:30"/>with the bare names of Faith, and Repentance, though they haue no true ſignes of faith, and repentance, though they bee neither ſeaſoned with the ſpirit of Grace, nor weaponed with ſpirituall ſtrength to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the aduerſaries of the ſoule, nor fruitfull in faith, bringing forth aboundantly the fruits thereof: though they be neuer touched with inward griefe, nor reformed in their wayes: theſe are like the church of <hi>Sardi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 3.1.</note> they <hi>would haue a name that they liue, whereas they are dead.</hi> But let them bee warned neuer to aduenture to eate of this Sacrament, till they be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter prepared, &amp; be that in deed which they appeare to be. God delights not in ſuch ſeruants that preſume to walke in their
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:990:30"/>Maſters apparell: he will not be mocked with ſuch deceitfull formes.</p>
            <p>The third ſort that fayle in their Preparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are thoſe that ſay they loue God, and yet hate their neighbors, or if they loue them, it is not apparant, but their loue is vnder a ſhadow. If at any time wrong bee offered them, it cannot be borne, nor brooked, they cannot forgiue, and forget, corrupt nature hath ſo leſſoned them,<note place="margin">Veterem fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendo Iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am inuitas nouam.</note> that by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp one wrong, they thinke they open a ſluce for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of many more, nay, they hold it a ſigne of a poore, and a cowardly ſpirit. It is courage, and manlineſſe ſay they, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge iniuries and wrongs. Is it manlineſſe? Nay, it is fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:<note place="margin">Eccleſ 7.9.</note> 
               <hi>Anger</hi> (ſayth <hi>Salomon</hi>)
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:990:31"/>that is, deſire of Reuenge, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in the boſome of fooles.</hi> Nay, it is brutiſhneſſe; anger a dogge and he will flie in your face; touch an Aſſe, &amp; he will wince, and kicke,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and fling: 1. So doe theſe foole-hardie, and Beaſt-wittie-fellowes. Nay, it argues rottenneſſe at the core, as when a man cannot endure to be tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, it is a ſigne he is not ſound ſo not to endure a croſſe word without thoughts of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, is a ſigne of an vnſound and corrupt minde.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Others there be that neuer will make amends, or reſtitution to their neighbour, but ſeeke for more, and like <hi>Pharoahs</hi> ſeuen leane kine would deuour as much as they could lay their hands on.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Others in ſtead of doing one good turne for another, inuent
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:990:31"/>what miſchiefe they can againſt their neighbours, they render euill for good, and ſeeke to harme them of whom they haue receiued good. 4.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Others when they ſhould prepare co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and cures for the offences of their neighbours, as faſt as they breed them (being offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces through infirmity) lay them in the open Sunne, and make publike Proclamation of them. 5. Others, will forgiue,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> but not forget, if they ſee their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in neede, they will not hurt him, but paſſe by, like the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and the <hi>Leuite,</hi> and doe him no good. 6. Others,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> will doe no hurt, yea, they will doe good to their neighbour. How? They will pray for them. In what manner? that they were in Heauen. Alas, poore ſoule,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:990:32"/>thou prayeſt not ſo much that he may liue in heauen, as that he may leaue the earth: not ſo much that he might enioy that life, as be depriued of this, which is murther in ſome ſort. 7.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Others, can reioyce with their neighbours in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie, but forſake them in aduerſitie: theſe are like Mice, that will come to a Barne when there is ſtore of Corne in it, but when the Corne is gone, they are gone alſo, which ſheweth that they came not for loue of the Barne, but of the Corne. So many loue their neighbors onely for that which they haue. 8.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Others, are ſo farre from a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fellow-feeling of their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours miſerie, that they inſult ouer them, adding affliction to the afflicted; &amp; reioyce in their
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:990:32"/>diſtreſſe, as the <hi>Edomites</hi> in the day of the deſtruction, and cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie of <hi>Iudah.</hi> 9.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Others, though they reioyce not at, yet they are no way touched with their neighbours calamitie, and when they ſhould put to their helping hand, they anſwer with <hi>Cain, What am I my brothers kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per?</hi> They feaſt it themſelues,<note place="margin">Amos 6.4.</note> but <hi>are not grieued for the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Ioſeph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe which reſpect not their neighbours good, nor practiſe loue, and charitie, muſt not preſume to eate of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> which is a feaſt of charitie. That meate is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, which is eaten with a malicious ſtomacke, and grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gingly digeſted, much leſſe good, will the Sacrament of the bodie and bloud of Chriſt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:990:33"/>bring to him that is cloyed with malice, enuie, hatred, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite, grudges, and murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings. The time that Chriſt was conuerſant with his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, he taught them humilitie, patience, contempt of the world, and other Chriſtian ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues: but the perſwaſion of loue, charitie, and good will he reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to his laſt Supper, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent they might vnderſtand that feaſt to be a feaſt of loue, and charitie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third dutie that euery one muſt looke vnto, that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth to be haue himſelfe well before he receiue, is <hi>Knowledge,</hi> whereby hee ſhall bee able in ſome meaſure, to know, and diſcerne that thing aright, which he intends to receiue. This is very neceſſary if it bee
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:990:33"/>ſound: firſt, becauſe then it is a ſanctified vnderſtanding of the diuine myſteries, and alſo of all Principles of Religion, as firſt, Of the Trinitie of perſons, in the Vnitie of the God-head ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, Of the creation of man and his fall: thirdly, Of the curſe, and miſerie due to ſinne: fourthly, of the natures and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of Chriſt, and redemption by faith in his death, eſpecially of the doctrine of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſealing the ſame vnto vs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If we know not GODS will in theſe myſteries, wee can neither beleeue, nor receiue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right: Buſineſſes cannot bee done by them, that haue no skil in them. So without skill in theſe ſpirituall matters, wee are far off from good concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:990:34"/>3. To receiue without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, is to crucifie Chriſt, to wound, and peirce him againe, which brings damnation to the ignorant perſon, as <hi>Paul</hi> well obſerueth in his firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.27.29.</note> 
               <hi>Who ſoeuer ſhall eate theſe holy things vnworthily, not diſcerning the Lords bodie, is both guiltie of the bodie and bloud of Chriſt,</hi> and alſo draweth downe damnation vpon himſelfe.</p>
            <p>The vſe of this poynt may teach vs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 1.</note> that there is no roome in this feſtiuall meeting, for children in vnderſtanding, who in their pure naturalls are farre off from comprehending the vſe, and end of this Sacrament. Secondly, Here is no place for naturall fooles, or mad-men, they are ſimple, but yet wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that Doue-like ſimplicitie,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:990:34"/>which is requiſite to this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, they muſt be debarred. Thirdly, nor for ſicke men that are paſt their ſenſes: Fourthly, nor for ignorant men, though they be come to ſome ripeneſſe in age, and yeares.</p>
            <p n="2">2. All Miniſters, Parents,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 2.</note> and Tutors may iuſtly bee blamed, that admit, ſuffer, and ſend ſuch ſenſeleſſe people to this feaſt, when beſt wits, and the greateſt vnderſtanding is all little e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 3.</note> let all Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters learne hence a leſſon. <hi>None can come vnto God but they muſt firſt know God,</hi> therefore it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth them to Catechize ſuch as purpoſe to receiue, that triall may be made of their knowledge. I know many lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Maſters will thinke ſcorne,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:990:35"/>that their ſeruants, or their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhould be inſtructed, yet let not great words daſh the Miniſter out of countenance, it is better, he fulfill his dutie in Catechiſing, then finde the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the Lord kindled againſt him for his negligence.</p>
            <p>The things wherein our knowledge muſt be exerciſed in this Sacrament, are 1. the parts of it: 2. the vſe and end of it. 3. what it is to eate it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, for the parts of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, wee muſt know, that there be two; the outward ſigne and the inward grace: the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſignes are two, bread and wine; the inward Graces are two, the bodie and bloud of Chriſt. Bread is broken, rent, or torne in peeces, to ſignifie the rending, crucifying, tearing
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:990:35"/>or breaking in peeces the body of Chriſt vpon the Croſſe, to be a Propitiatorie ſacrifice for all our ſinnes:<note place="margin">Heb. 10.10</note> therefore Chriſt when he had giuen thankes, he brake the bread, and ſaid to his Diſciples, <hi>Take, eate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.24.</note> 
               <hi>this is my bodie which was broken for you.</hi> The powring of the Wine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to put vs in minde, that Chriſt was thruſt to a tree with a ſpeare,<note place="margin">Ioh: 19.1.2 &amp;c.</note> and ſo out of his ſides ſhed his moſt precious bloud for our ſins, therfore we are ſaid to haue <hi>Redemption by his bloud,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.7.</note> for without ſhedding of bloud, no remiſſion of ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Queſt.</note> But I would know why Chriſt choſe Bread, and Wine, rather then any other Element to be outward ſignes in this bleſſed Sacrament?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol:</hi> Firſt,<note place="margin">Sol.</note> becauſe they are ſoon
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:990:36"/>procured: ſecondly, to teach vs that as mans temporall life is chiefely nouriſhed by <hi>Bread,</hi> and cheriſhed by <hi>Wine,</hi> ſo are our ſoules by his bodie, and bloud ſuſtained, and quickened vnto eternall life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ob.</note> But why is Wine added to the Bread.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sol.</note> To teach vs, firſt, that as perfect nouriſhment of mans bodie conſiſts both of meate &amp; drinke: So Chriſt is vnto our ſoules, not in part, but in perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, both ſaluation, and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment: ſecondly, that by ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Wine</hi> apart from the <hi>Bread,</hi> wee ſhould remember how all his precious bloud was ſpilt out of his bleſſed body for the remiſſion of our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vſe.</note>This makes againſt that hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible ſacriledge of the Church
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:990:36"/>of <hi>Rome,</hi> who takes away, and denieth vnto the people, one part of this Sacrament, that is to ſay, the Wine, and miniſter it but vnder one kinde, vnder the Bread without the wine, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie vnto Chriſts inſtitution, who firſt tooke Bread, and then Wine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ob.</note> But are not the outward ſignes, ordinarie bread, and wine?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sol.</note> No. <hi>They are conſecrated by a diuine Word,</hi> which doth not change their ſubſtance into other ſubſtances, but changeth them in their vſe and name: for that which was before but common Bread, and Wine to nouriſh mens bodies, is after the bleſſing ſet apart to an holy vſe, for the feeding of the ſoules of Chriſtians. And where be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:990:37"/>they were called but bread and wine, they are now called by the names of thoſe holy things they ſignifie, <hi>the bodie and bloud of Chriſt:</hi> the better to draw our mindes from thoſe outward Elements to heauenly Graces, which by the ſight of our bodies they repreſent to the ſpirituall eyes of our faith.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond thing, that muſt be knowne, is the vſe, and end of this Sacrament: there be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe ends thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, it is ordained of God to ſhew vs the Lord his death: Chriſt when he had giuen the bread, and wine to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, bids them <hi>doe all in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk 12.19. Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.26 1. Cor. 11.26.</note> And <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth, <hi>as often as we eate this bread, and drinke of this cup, we ſhew forth the Lords death till he come.</hi> As
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:990:37"/>the ſtaying, and killing of the Paſchall Lambe was a notable meanes to ſhew the <hi>Lords</hi> death <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill he came in the fleſh; ſo this Sacrament is a ſpeciall meanes to ſhew vs his death alreadie come, and vnder-gone for vs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill ſuch time as he ſhall come againe to Iudge the world in righteouſneſſe: Hence the Lords Supper is called a Propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiatorie ſacrifice,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> not properly or really, but figuratiuely, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a memoriall of that Propitiatorie ſacrifice, which Chriſt offered vpon the croſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 1.</note> This doctrine ſerueth to confute, and ouerthrow the Popiſh Maſſe, wherein the Prieſt would repreſent Chriſt vnto the People: for this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is onely ordained of <hi>God,</hi> as a liuely meanes to repreſent
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:990:38"/>Chriſt, and to ſhew forth his death till he come, but yet they are not contented with this liuely repreſentation of Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> exhibited, but they haue brought in three more repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations, and ſo make foure in all;</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. <hi>Simplex repreſentatio,</hi> a ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple repreſentation of the death of Chriſt, which is done ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, as this Sacrament is recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. <hi>Repreſentatio ad viuem,</hi> a liuely, and full repreſentation of Chriſts death, which they doe vſe yearely to ſet forth by ſolemne geſtures, apparell, and other ceremonies vpon good Fryday, as it is commonly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led before Eaſter; and ſo they make this Sacrament nothing elſe, but a Pageant play.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:990:38"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. The third repreſentation, is their ſacrifice of the Maſſe.<note place="margin">Bellar: de Miſſa lib. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>And 4. the fourth is added by the Rhemiſts,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> who wiſhed that this Sacrament might bee celebrated at Eaſter,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rhemiſt.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.8.</note> and the reliques of it (if there were any) hanged vp in a Pixe, not onely to repreſent Chriſt, but to houſle the ſicke. But wee are taught by the word of God, that by eating the bread, and drinking the wine, and not by gazing, or looking on, or lifting vp, or turning about, or carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in proceſſions, or hanging vp bread in Pixes, or by any ſuch meanes is the Lords death ſhewed forth. We are to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge onely one Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall repreſentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the Supper,<note place="margin">Morna: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Miſſam cap: <hi>60.</hi>
               </note> and the ſacrifice of the Maſſe an abhominable
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:990:39"/>Idoll, neuer heard of till after the time of <hi>Gregorie</hi> the Great, in the fixt age of the Church.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by this point fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth to the ground another pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of Poperie, namely, their Tranſubſtantiation, whereby they hold the very Elements of bread and wine, to be changed into the very bodie, and bloud of Chriſt, and ſo maintaine the Phyſicall, ſubſtantiall, and reall preſence: but if the end of this Sacrament be to ſhew forth Chriſts death, and all that wee muſt doe, <hi>muſt be done in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of him,</hi> then Chriſt is not really, or phyſically preſent: Helpes of remembrance are of things abſent, not preſent, and therefore <hi>Gelaſius</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Lib: de dua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Chriſti naturis.</note> Bread and Wine in this Sacrament paſſe into the bodie and bloud
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:990:39"/>of Chriſt, yet ſo, as the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and nature of Bread and Wine ceaſeth not. <hi>Bernard</hi> could ſay, Chriſt is preſent, <hi>Non materiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſed ſpiritualiter,</hi> not ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially, but by a Sacramentall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation betweene the ſignes, and the things ſignified.</p>
            <p>This Popiſh tradition was not known in the primitiue church nor long after. Which makes <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſay thus;<note place="margin">Ignatius in Epiſt: ad Philadelph:</note> 
               <hi>There is one fleſh of our Lord, and one bloud ſhed for vs, one bread broken for all, and one cup for the whole Church;</hi> how was it poſſible bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to diſtinguiſh betweene the ſignes, and the thing ſignified, then by theſe foure words; firſt, <hi>fleſh,</hi> and ſecondly, <hi>bloud</hi> on the one part; thirdly, <hi>bread,</hi> and fourthly, <hi>cup,</hi> on the other part. This point is handled elſwhere
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:990:40"/>in one Treatiſe of the doctrine of this Sacrament.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond end of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament is to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme our faith, in which reſpect it is called a <hi>ſeale of the new couenant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.28 Rom. 4.11. 1 Cor. 11.25.</note> 
               <hi>and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion of ſinnes,</hi> and alſo to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure vs of life eternall, in which reſpect it is called,<note place="margin">Reu. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>the tree of life, which God hath planted in the midſt of the Paradiſe of his Church, and whereof he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to giue euery one that ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth to eate.</hi> Our Sauiour aſſureth vs,<note place="margin">Ioh: 6.5.</note> that <hi>if any man eate of this bread he ſhall liue for euer, and the bread that I will giue him is my fleſh, which I will giue for the life of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ob.</note> Yea, but wee haue the word to confirme our faith, and to aſſure vs of our ſaluation, what need we this Sacrament?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:990:40"/>
               <hi>Sol:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sol.</note> Though wee haue the word, yet this Sacrament is needfull, and in two things it goeth beyond the word.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. In this Sacrament God offers, and exhibites Chriſt, and his benefits to euery faithfull Communicant: Not onely ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally as the word doth, but alſo particularly, therefore hee ſayth, <hi>Take thou this, eate thou this, &amp;c.</hi> But in the word hee ſpeakes, and offers Chriſt one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly generally to all that beleeue, and repent, ctc.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. In the word he giueth but onely his promiſe of grace, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Chriſt, and his benefits: but in this ſacrament he giueth not onely his promiſe of grace, and that in particular, but alſo his ſeale, and pledge for the further ratifying, and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:990:41"/>of his promiſe, therefore it is ſaid, <hi>This is my bodie; &amp;c.</hi> This then muſt needes much confirme our faith,<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> as we ſee the Kings great broad ſeale ſet to a pardon, confirmeth a pardon: the matter of the ſeale of Gods Couenant, conſiſteth not, (as doe the ſeales of Kings and Princes of the earth) either of yellow, or red, or greene waxe, but of the red bloud, of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maculate Lambe Ieſus Chriſt, which is viſible, exhibited to the eye of faith; for which cauſe the Lord himſelfe, and the Apoſtle calleth the Cup in this Supper, <hi>the bloud of the new Teſtament,</hi> or of the new Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, for that couenant of grace is ratified, eſtabliſhed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, yea, and ſealed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, as it were with the Lords broad ſeale.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:990:41"/>And as in the Kings broad ſeale, there is imprinted, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauen, and liuely repreſented the perſon of his Maieſtie: So in this Sacrament, which is the Lords ſeale, is imprinted, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauen, and repreſented the verie bodie &amp; bloud of Chriſt, and the liuely perſon of the ſonne of God: and all for the ſtrengthening of our faith, and the nouriſhing vp of our ſoules in the aſſurance of our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, through his merites and mediation.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. A third end of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, is to be a token of our Vnion with Chriſt, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with our brethren;</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of our Vnion with Chriſt, <hi>The Cup of bleſsing which wee bleſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.16.</note> 
               <hi>is it not the communion of the bloud of Chriſt? and the bread
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:990:42"/>which we breake is it not the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the bodie of Chriſt?</hi> That is, a moſt effectuall ſigne and pledge of our vnion with Chriſt. This vnion is called, <hi>abiding in vs:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 14.16.23. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>a ioyning to the Lord: a dwelling in our hearts,</hi> and is wrought betwixt Chriſt and vs,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.17 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Epheſ. 3.7. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> by the ſpirit of Chriſt, apprehending vs, and by our faith (ſtirred vp by the ſame ſpirit) apprehending Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Both which S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth moſt liuely expreſſe: <hi>I follow after,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>if that I may apprehend that for which alſo I am apprehended of Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> This vnion is beſt felt and moſt confirmed when we doe duely receiue the Lords ſupper: for then we ſhall feele ſenſibly our hearts knit vnto Chriſt, and the deſires of our ſoules drawne by faith, and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:990:42"/>the holy Ghoſt, as by the cords of loue nearer, and nearer to his holineſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Of our Communion with our brethren:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.17.</note> 
               <hi>We being many are one bread, and one bodie:</hi> for wee are all partakers of that one bread; that as the bread which we eate in the Sacrament is but one, though it be made of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny graines: So all the faithfull though they be many, yet are they but one myſticall bodie vnder one head, which is Chriſt. This Communion plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Chriſt very well,<note place="margin">Ioh: 17.11 21.22.23.26.</note> elſe hee would not haue prayed for it ſo often as he did: and it is highly commended in the Primitiue Church, becauſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers were of one heart, and of one ſoule in truth, affection, and compaſſion.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:990:43"/>4. A fourth end of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament is a token and pledge of our 1. ſpirituall reſurrection. <hi>He that eateth me ſhall liue, bleſſed be that man that hath part in this reſurrection.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh: 6.57.</note> 2. Of our corporall Reſurrection,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="54"/> 
               <hi>He that eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my bloud hath eternall life, and I will raiſe him vp at the laſt day.</hi> Chriſt our head is riſen, therefore all the members of the bodie ſhall likewiſe riſe: for how can thoſe <hi>bodies which are weapons of righteouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.13.</note> 
               <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1 Cor. 6.19.</hi> Iuo modo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant carnem capacem eſſe reſurrectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, quae ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſti nutritur? Irenae: lib: <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> and haue beene fed and nouriſhed with the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and bloud of the Lord of life, but be raiſed vp againe at the laſt day?</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third, and laſt thing which muſt be knowne touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this ſupper,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> before we come
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:990:43"/>to it, is this: Wee muſt know what it is to eate this Supper: many are ignorant in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: Now to eate this Supper is to eate the fleſh of Chriſt, and to drinke his bloud ſpiritually by faith, vnder the ſignes of bread and wine: for this cauſe Chriſt ſayth, <hi>I am the bread of life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh: 6.35.</note> 
               <hi>he that commeth to mee ſhall not hunger, &amp;c.</hi> And againe, <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept yee eate the fleſh of the ſonne of man, and drinke his bloud,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="53"/> 
               <hi>ye haue no life in you.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="54"/> Againe, <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer eateth my fleſh, and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth my bloud, hath eternall life,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="55"/> 
               <hi>for my fleſh is meate indeede, and my bloud is drinke indeede.</hi> And all this muſt bee done by faith, which is both the hand, mouth, and ſtomacke of the ſoule, to receiue, chaw, and digeſt this heauenly foode.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:990:44"/>In the Goſpell of S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> it is ſaid, that God giueth this pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge to ſo many, as receiue Chriſt, <hi>that they are the ſonnes of God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh: 1.12.</note> and a little after it is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who receiue Chriſt, namely, <hi>all thoſe that doe truely beleeue.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> So that looke as the hand of the bodie takes the bread, and the wine, and the mouth chaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and the ſtomacke digeſteth them, to the refreſhing, and nouriſhing of the bodie: euen ſo faith as the hand of the ſoule taketh hold vpon Chriſt repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, and reſembled vnder the ſignes of bread and wine, and feedeth vpon him, ſo as both ſoule and bodie are fed, and nouriſhed vnto eternall life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ob.</note> But our bodily foode is preſent with vs, Chriſt is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:990:44"/>how then can we feed on him?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sol.</note> I anſwere, that it is true he is in heauen, for the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſayth,<note place="margin">Act. 3.21.</note> 
               <hi>the heauens muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine him till the reſtoring of all things:</hi> Yet notwithſtanding, he may be ſaid to be really pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent two wayes. 1. To the ſignes by a Sacramentall relation. 2. to the Communicants by faith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.<note place="margin">Fidem mitte in coelum &amp; eum interris tanquam preſentem te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuiſti. Aug. Epiſt. <hi>3.</hi> ad Voluſ:</note> In the holy Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of faith, thou art at one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant with Chriſt, and Chriſt with thee.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi> Seeing Chriſt is offered in this Sacrament to bee our foode: and we are to feede ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually on his bodie, and bloud in aſſurance of life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, this then muſt teach vs to be carefull to keepe our ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mackes for this meate, and not
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:990:45"/>cloy them before hand with ſinne. Men commonly keepe their ſtomackes for the beſt meate, and will not cloy them with the meaneſt: ſo let vs keep our ſtomackes for this bleſſed <hi>Manna,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 78.24 25.</note> which will make vs looke freſh in this worldly wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe.<note place="margin">Num. 16.35.</note> 
               <hi>Labour not</hi> (ſayth our Sauiour) <hi>ſo much for the meate that periſheth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh: 6.27.</note> 
               <hi>as for that which will laſt for euer.</hi> And that our ſtomackes may be fit for this <hi>heauenly bread,</hi> and <hi>Lordly cup,</hi> we muſt take heed of ſinne: we are called, <hi>the Temples of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> let vs looke that theſe temples be cleane ſwept, and cleanſed, otherwiſe neither Chriſt, nor the holy Ghoſt will come into them.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> 2. This ſheweth vs, how need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a thing faith is, to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:990:45"/>of this Sacrament. All this meate in this Supper muſt be eaten by faith. As meate will doe one no good that wants hand, mouth, and ſtomacke; ſo this meate cannot profit any, that wanteth faith.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If we haue not the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of faith, this Supper ſeales nothing vnto vs, <hi>Euery man receiueth as much, as he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eeueth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Without faith we cannot apprehend Chriſt in heauen: (we being on earth,) for as he dwelleth in vs by faith, ſo by faith we muſt likewiſe eate him.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note>3. Without faith we cannot be perſwaded in our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that our receiuing is <hi>accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14.23</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ob:</note> Are none but the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full nouriſhed in this Supper,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:990:46"/>are not the wicked nouriſhed a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> well as they?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sol:</note> No. 1. They haue no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> part in Chriſt: He would not pray for them.<note place="margin">Ioh: 17.9.</note> 2. Wanting faith, they are no welcome gueſts to this banquet.<note place="margin">Panem Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, non pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Aug. de Iuda.</note> 3. They may eate the Lords bread, but not that bread which is the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ob.</note> What doe the wicked receiue in this Sacrament? I am ſure they receiue the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sol.</note> Surely they receiue the Elements onely, and encreaſe of more vngodlineſſe, &amp; more fulneſſe of all iniquitie, euill men,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.13.</note> and deceiuers are ſayd to waxe worſe and worſe, as <hi>Iudas</hi> ſo ſoone as he had receiued this ſacrament, grew forthwith miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieuous:<note place="margin">Ioh: 13.27.</note> Sathan entred into
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:990:46"/>him, and filled him full of all iniquitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ob.</note> Then it ſeemeth the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament is not in vaine to any?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sol.</note> No indeed; for, as it is a ſeale of ſaluation to the godly, ſo it is a ſeale of condemnation to all the wicked: and a token of Gods vengeance.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth and laſt dutie in our behauiour before wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, is a longing deſire, and an hungrie appetite after that we are about to receiue in this Sacrament; this dutie is well added to the former: for,<note place="margin">Knowledge and deſire muſt be ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</note> 
               <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> and <hi>deſiring</hi> are ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. A man can neither know Chriſt truly, but he muſt needes deſire, and long after him: neither can he deſire, and long after him, till he firſt know him: Here is the triall of our
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:990:47"/>knowledge. It is but vaine, and trifling knowledge, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoketh not to deſire. If our eyes were opened to ſee, then our mouthes would cry after Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Ignorant perſons muſt here take notice of their miſerie;<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> for not knowing Chriſt, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deſire him, nor deſiring him, they cannot enioy him. If euer thou wouldeſt haue thy ſoule thriue, labour to haue thine eyes opened to ſee the worth of Chriſts merit,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.18</note> and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. This is the reaſon why ſo few pray, and heartily deſire to be partaker of this Supper, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they know not the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof.<note place="margin">The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the word, &amp; the Sacrament is this, the word is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>verbum audibile,</hi> the Sacrament, <hi>verbum viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile. Aug.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>This fourth dutie (next vnto knowledge) is an earneſt deſire to Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate, as if a drought
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:990:47"/>had ouertaken vs, and our ſoules began to be parched, for want of moyſture. As <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeakes of the word <hi>Audible,</hi> ſo it may be ſayd of the word <hi>Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> Before we come to the Word, wee muſt prepare our ſelues by <hi>laying aſide all malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>And as new borne babes we muſt deſire the ſincere milke of the word, that we may grow thereby.</hi> So we muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare before wee come to this Sacrament, and lay away all our ſinnes: then as new borne babes, we muſt cry, hunger, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hirſt, after the body and bloud of Chriſt, the food of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oules.</p>
            <p>Now this longing deſire, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ungring appetite muſt ariſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom a 1. ſenſe, and feeling of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur want of Chriſt; 2. and from
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:990:48"/>the weakeneſſe of our faith. <hi>Paul</hi> ſeeing a great want of Chriſt in himſelfe, and the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute neceſſitie of euery drop of his bloud to waſh away his ſinnes, deſired aboue all things to <hi>winne Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.8.9.</note> 
               <hi>and to be found in him,</hi> yea, he <hi>accounted all things as droſſe and dung,</hi> to the end he might obtaine him.</p>
            <p>There be ſundry reaſons why this Sacrament ſhould be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red:<note place="margin">Reaſons.</note> ſome concerne men of knowledge: others belong in generall to all.</p>
            <p>Firſt, there be good reaſons of deſiring this Sacrament in them that know the parts, end, and vſe thereof.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. They conceiue this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament to be a ſeale <hi>of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe by faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4.11.</note> an aſſurance of our Vnion with Chriſt, for
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:990:48"/>which cauſe it muſt needes bee ſweete vnto their ſoules.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They apprehend it to be a badge of their profeſſion of their Religion, and of their ſeruice to Chriſt, and therefore they cannot but deſire it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They beleeue it to be the band of the communion of the Saints, and in that reſpect they muſt needs affect it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They know Chriſt is therein ſpecially preſent with his ſpirit of grace, and all ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall benefits, and therefore they long after it.</p>
            <p>The reaſons that concerne all men generally are theſe;</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. The food in this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will doe them moſt good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat haue moſt deſire to it; euen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s we ſee meate is beſt to them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat haue good ſtomackes to
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:990:49"/>receiue it: as for thoſe that want ſtomackes it doth them more harme then good.<note place="margin">Luk. 1.53.</note> 
               <hi>The hungry are filled, but the rich,</hi> and thoſe that want ſtomackes, <hi>are ſent emptie away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. God maketh all his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of grace, and mercie one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to thoſe that hunger, and thirſt after Chriſt, and his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits offered in this Sacrament: Our asking, and Gods giuing; our opening the mouth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 81.10.</note> and his filling; our thirſting, and his watering; our open heart, and his open hand goe together: If Gods hand be ſhut, it is becauſe thine heart is ſhut; God will not giue without asking; If thou haue no mouth to aske, God hath no hand to giue, On the contrary, if thou haue an heart ful of deſires, thou haſt
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:990:49"/>an aſſurance of receiuing thy deſires: thy requeſt can bee no ſooner in Gods eare, but Gods hand is in thine heart. Euen in thy ſighs, and deſires for grace, thou ſhalt finde comfort, and ioy, for in deſiring thou ſhalt receiue.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed are they that hunger and thirſt, for they ſhall be ſatisfied: If any thirſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh: 7.37.38.</note> 
               <hi>let him come to the waters, he ſhall drinke, and out of his belly ſhall ſlow riuers of waters:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 55.1.2. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Ho euery one that thirſteth come to the waters, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. They which haue no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to this Sacrament are in the ſtate of a ſick man, who though his bodie be leane, and readie to periſh, yet his ſtomacke loatheth the meate, that is offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to him, to reſtore his health and to ſtrengthen him, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt ſayd of ſuch,<note place="margin">Iohn 5.</note> that
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:990:50"/>they would not come vnto him (being the ſpirituall poole of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> able to cure and heale all ſoule-diſeaſes) that they might haue life.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi> This ſheweth that the ſtate and condition of all thoſe that come not to this holy Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and yet preach vnto the world, that they want this hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, is very dangerous, and fearefull, for it argueth plainly, that they haue ſicke and leane ſoules, though healthfull, and fat bodies: their faith and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is almoſt, if not altogether dead; and except they get ſome good helpe in ſome ſeaſonable time, they will vtterly periſh.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Here is a cooler to the itch of ambition, to the thirſt of couetouſneſſe:<note place="margin">Iſa. 55.2.</note> 
               <hi>Why lay you out your money, and not for bread,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:990:50"/>and your labour without being ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied?</hi> Our ſoule can finde no more reſt in any earthly thing, then <hi>Noahs</hi> Doue out of the Arke, therefore as ſhe returned to the Arke; ſo muſt thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to God that made thee for himſelfe. The circular world cannot fill the triangular heart, no more then a Circle can fill a triangle, ſtill there will be ſome emptie corners. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can fill the heart but that fulneſſe which is in Ieſus. And therefore purſue thy deſires, theſe earthly things as earneſtly as thou wilt, and get of them what thou canſt, and delight thy ſelfe in thy fooles Paradiſe, promiſing this, and that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, in the end thy thirſt will be greater then it was in the beginning, thy bread will
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:990:51"/>proue grauell, thy honie gall, thy wine vineger, thy fiſh Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents.<note place="margin">Ipſa etiam vota poſt v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum faſtidio ſunt, &amp; quae mereri opta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uimus, vbi meruerimus abdicamus.</note> All earthly things are ſweeter in the ambition, then in the fruition. After the vſe, we e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen loath the things, that wee haue often deſired, and thoſe things that we haue deſired to obtaine, when wee haue obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, we reiect.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> 3. Take notice of the great lets, and many impediments of this ſpirituall thirſt, and long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſire.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. The firſt is Ignorance, men know not, therefore they affect not Chriſt in this Sacrament: <hi>If thou hadſt knowne the gift of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh: 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>thou wouldeſt haue asked, and he would haue giuen thee waters of life.</hi> Becauſe men ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not diſcerne with the eye of ſenſe this ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall water, they neuer affect,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:990:51"/>nor thirſt after it, whence it comes to paſſe, that they ſtand (as it were with <hi>Tantalus,</hi> of whom the Poet ſpeakes) vp to the chin in water, &amp; yet die for water, they ſit (as it were) in the midſt of a richly furniſhed Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and yet pine away for want of cheare. If we want them it is becauſe we do not hunger and thirſt after them, for onely he that hungreth and thirſteth is called to them, and Chriſt will only giue to him that hungreth and thirſteth to eate, &amp; drinke of them.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. The ſecond im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment, is <hi>hardneſſe of heart,</hi> this is worſe then the former, for that cannot affect becauſe it knoweth not, this will not tho it know. It is an hard matter to get a drop of water out of a flint and as hard a matter to ſoften
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:990:52"/>it, though riuers of waters be powred on it: So it is with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a man, the hardneſſe of his heart is ſo inuincible, that it cannot relent, neither will one drop of the dewes of Heauen peirce it further then the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, like the heate of the Sunne that getteth not further into the tree then the outſide.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third is ſecuritie ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with extreme neglect, men are careleſſe of the benefits that may be reaped in this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo caſt it off: like a begger that might grow to ſome better eſtate, yet caſtes vp all care, foldeth his hands to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, putteth them into his boſome, and lets the ſquares goe as they will.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> 4 <hi>Vſe.</hi> Let vs thirſt after Chriſt in this Sacrament exhibited to
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:990:52"/>beleeuers:<note place="margin">Pſal. 42.1.</note> 
               <hi>as the heart panteth after the water brookes, ſo let our ſoules pant after him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ariſtot: de Hiſtoria ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malium lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi> Lucretius lib. <hi>6.</hi> Oppianus lib: <hi>2.</hi> de Venatione.</note> The Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers obſerue of the Hart, that being purſued by dogs in hunting, by reaſon of heat, and loſſe of breath, he haſteneth to the Riuers, or wearied in fight with a Serpent, or ſtung, or wounded by him, while the Serpent reſteth on the ground, he ſeeketh to ſome colde foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, whereby the infection of the venome receiued, may bee abated. Euen ſo ſuch as are wounded, and ſtrucken of the old ſerpent, muſt haue recourſe vnto Chriſt, not onely to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him with the eye of faith, but alſo to take him, and taſte him, by the hand, &amp; ſtomacke of faith, that they may be hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: For, he is the fountaine,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:990:53"/>and head-ſpring of all grace, it is he that ſendeth life, ſenſe, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and direction into all his members, reſembled in that <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oyntment which ran downe from Aarons head and beard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 133.2.</note> 
               <hi>euen to the skirts of his garment.</hi> He is that bleſſed bread in this ſacrament, which being worthily eaten, openeth the eyes of the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Hee is that <hi>Rocke flowing with Honey,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 14.27.</note> that reuiueth the fainting ſpirits of euery true <hi>Ionathan</hi> that taſtes it with the mouth of faith. He is the true <hi>Bread of life,</hi> and heauenly <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> which if we ſhall duely eate will nouriſh our ſoules for euer, <hi>vnto life eternall.</hi> How ſhould then our ſoules make vnto Chriſt, that requeſt from a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall deſire, which the Caper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naites did from a carnall moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?<note place="margin">Ioh: 6.34.</note>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:990:53"/>
               <hi>Lord euermore giue vs this bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſpeciall meanes to come by this hunger, and thirſt, is, a conſideration of mans miſerie, and Gods mercie; the way to diſcerne this hunger and thirſt is by the ſignes thereof; 1. By a ſenſe of paine in the ſtomacke: 2. By a want, and emptineſſe: 3. By an eager deſire of a ſupply. Thus much of the duties tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching our good behauiour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we receiue.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſort of duties in our good behauiour at the time of receiuing, follow in order: They are foure,</p>
            <p n="1">1. We are to receiue this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament as an inſtrument ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of God, to conuay Chriſt, and his benefits vnto vs, if we beleeue.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:990:54"/>2. Wee muſt receiue it with feare, and reuerence, ſeeing it is Gods ordinance, yet not to adore, and worſhip it, ſeeing it is not God, but his ordinance.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We muſt make a particular application thereof to our ſelues.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We muſt receiue it with ioy and delight.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> FIrſt we muſt receiue this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament being prepared, and preſenting our ſelues ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, not onely as a ſigne, to ſignifie Chriſt, and his benefits: but alſo as a voluntarie Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 2.13.</note> appoynted of God, for the conuaying of ſauing grace into our hearts. I call it a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarie Inſtrument, becauſe it is the will, and appoyntment of
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:990:54"/>God to vſe it, as a certaine out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward meanes of grace. It is an Inſtrument, becauſe when wee vſe it aright, according to <hi>Gods</hi> inſtitution, then God anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by it conferreth grace vnto vs. It may be ſayd to be an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to conferre Grace two wayes. 1. By the ſignification thereof. 2. By the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, By the ſignification thereof, for, God teſtifieth his good will, and pleaſure, partly by the word of promiſe, partly by the Sacrament. The ſignes repreſenting to the eyes, that which the word to the cares: being alſo types, and certaine Images of the very ſame things that are promiſed in the Word, yea, in this Sacrament. The ſignes are not generall, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:990:55"/>but particular to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Communicants.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. This Sacrament is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of confirming Grace, in that the ſignes thereof con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme our faith, as a pledge, by reaſon they haue the promiſe of God annexed thereunto. For when God commandeth vs to receiue the ſignes by faith, and promiſeth withall to giue the things ſignified, he bindeth himſelfe, as it were, in a bond vnto vs, to ſtand to his owne word, euen as men binde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in Obligations, putting to it their hands, and ſeales, ſo as they cannot goe backe: when the ſignes are thus vſed as pled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, then they are Inſtruments, not onely of the encreaſe, but alſo of the confirmation of Grace in vs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:990:55"/>This confirmation is on this wiſe, the ſignes, and outward Elements: 1. affect the ſenſes outward, and inward: 2. the ſenſes conuay the obiect to the minde: 3. the minde directly by the holy Ghoſt reaſoneth on this manner, out of the promiſe annexed to the Sacrament: He that receiueth the Elements a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, ſhall receiue confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Grace thereby: but I vſe them aright in faith and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, ſayth the minde of the beleeuer, therefore I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue confirmation, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi> This ſerueth to confute the Papiſts, who hold both this Sacrament, and the other of Baptiſme, not to be voluntarie Inſtruments of God to confer Grace, but naturall, and Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Inſtruments, hauing power
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:990:56"/>and efficacie to work,<note place="margin">Bellarm: de ſacram: lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap: <hi>4.11.</hi>
               </note> produce, and giue grace, yea, that the very action of the Miniſter, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing the Sacrament, <hi>Ex ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re operato,</hi> giueth grace imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, as the moouing of the Pen cauſeth writing. This Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh doctrine is fearefully dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie from the bloud of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Si quis dixe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit per ipſa nouae legis ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenta ex opere operato non conferri gratia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. Concil: Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den: ſeſſ: <hi>7.</hi> Can: <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> &amp; contrary to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: For, 1. this effect cannot be aſcribed to the worke done as they teach: 2. neither can any extraordinary eleuation of their Beeaden-God conferre grace, for this were to make the Sacrament a miracle, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croach vpon the right of the holy Ghoſt: 3. neither haue the outward elements any inherent: force, and power to feede the ſoule, as they haue to feed the bodie: 4. neither becauſe grace
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:990:56"/>is not tyed by any promiſe, or meanes to the action, ſo as God who is moſt free in his gifts, cannot either otherwiſe diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, or cannot otherwiſe but diſpence it with the action.</p>
            <p>But vnderſtand, that 1. Grace is not tyed to the word, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to this Sacrament.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If this were true, then euery Communicant ſhould be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, the contrary whereof ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in many of <hi>Pauls</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> 3. <hi>Paul</hi> ſtands much vpon this, to proue, that Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by faith is not confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Sacrament, &amp; from circumſtance of time gathereth that <hi>Abraham</hi> was firſt iuſtified, before he receiued the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:<note place="margin">Act. 10.47.</note> So <hi>Cornelius</hi> did truely feare God, and was endued with the ſpirit of prayer: So
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:990:57"/>the <hi>Eunuch</hi> was firſt a beleeuer,<note place="margin">Act. 8.37.38.</note> before hee Communicated:</p>
            <p n="4">4. This opinion of tying grace to the Sacrament, ouerthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, 1. the higheſt and moſt proper cauſe of our ſaluation, which is Gods free election, to which onely Grace is tyed: 2. the onely meritorious cauſe which is the bloud of Chriſt: 3. the moſt powerfull, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying efficient, which is the holy Ghoſt, to whom Grace is aſcribed, and not to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 2. As it is with the Lords Supper, ſo it is with all other ordinances of God, no outward means can be effectuall, vnleſſe the inward worke of the ſpirit be added. We haue power to come, and heare the word, but vnleſſe the <hi>anoynting teach vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ioh: 2.27.</note>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:990:57"/>we ſhall remaine vntaught: yea let the Apoſtles themſelues preach,<note place="margin">Mar. 16.20.</note> the <hi>Lord muſt worke</hi> with them alſo, or nothing can be done. Wee haue power to come to Baptiſme, yet vnleſſe we be renewed <hi>by the holy Ghoſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 3.5.</note> and <hi>the ſpirit be vpon vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 59.21.</note> the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward water will doe no good. If there be any grace in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (ſayth <hi>Baſil</hi>) it is not in the nature of the water,<note place="margin">Baſil: lib. <hi>de</hi> Spiritu San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto cap. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> but from the preſence of the ſpirit; and <hi>Hierome</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Hieron. in Iſa. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> man giueth wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but God giueth the holy Ghoſt. Let vs beware and take heede, that we giue not too much to outward meanes, as if they ſhuld yeeld forth all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable fruit, and all efficacie, of themſelues without the worke of the ſpirit. Many boaſt of the Sacrament very much
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:990:58"/>(as the <hi>Iewes</hi> of their Temple, the Law, Circnmciſion, Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, &amp;c.) yet if they goe no further then the outward ſigne, it cannot be an Inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t from God to conuay grace into their hearts. As of Baptiſme, ſo it may be ſayd of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per:<note place="margin">Vis regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randi non a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quae ſimplici, ſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentali, ideſt gratiae Dei, quae median<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae verbo, per aquam ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur adſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benda eſt. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan: in Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſ. Cateck: Baſil.</note> the efficacie, and ſtrength of our regeneration, and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation cannot be aſcribed to the bare ſigne, but to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall ſigne; that is, to the grace of God, working with the outward ſigne, yet ſo that the word of God muſt worke with them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond dutie touching our behauiour, in the time of receiuing, is this, We muſt ſet our ſelues in the ſight, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord, and receiue this Sacrament with feare, and
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:990:58"/>reuerence, as Gods owne ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, to conuay, encreaſe, and to confirme Grace in vs, ſo, as that we muſt not worſhip it as God himſelfe, the author, and beſtower of all grace, &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>Take heede</hi> (ſayth <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>) <hi>to thy foote, when thou en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſt into the houſe of God, and be more readie to heare, then to offer the ſacrifice of fooles, for they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider not that they doe euill:</hi> as this muſt be done at the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the Word, ſo at the reſt of all Gods ordinances: for this is a moſt certain rule, that what feare, and reuerence, God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth in one of his ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, he requireth in all his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances. Hee would haue vs to feare and tremble at the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of them.<note place="margin">Iſa. 66.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The ground,<note place="margin">Reaſon.</note> and Reaſon is,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:990:59"/>becauſe that abuſe which is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vnto any of Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, the Lord taketh as done vnto himſelfe; euen as the Prince taketh that diſgrace, which is done to his Crowne, and robes, as done to himſelfe. Chriſt ſayth, thoſe that deſpiſe his Miniſters, deſpiſe him, and thoſe that deſpiſe him, deſpiſe his Father that ſent him: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all our geſtures, &amp; behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, muſt be ſuch, as ſhew forth a feare, and reuerence due vnto God in reſpect of his ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, whither we receiue it kneeling, ſitting, or ſtanding, or the like, yet (theſe things being in diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues) we muſt haue a reſpect vnto the order, &amp; rule of comelines, which is ſet down in the Church wherin we liue, becauſe ſo much as poſſibly we
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:990:59"/>can, we are to keepe the vnitie, and peace of the Church: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes prouided, that nothing be done in way of religious ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring, and worſhipping the ſacrament, which were to make the creature a Creator. God onely is to be worſhipped and ſerued;<note place="margin">Mat. 4.10.</note> as our Sauiour anſwered Sathan, when he would haue had him to haue fallen downe, and worſhipped him.<note place="margin">A Cerere, &amp; Baccho Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganorum dijs longe abſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uis panis et cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum noſtro ritu amplec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timur. Aug. ad Fauſt.</note> We muſt not worſhip (ſaith one) the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Gods of bread and wine, though after our maner we em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the ſacrament of bread &amp; wine: his meaning is that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians doe not worſhip bread &amp; wine, as the heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s did. A holy <hi>Martyr</hi> well anſwered his Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponents,<note place="margin">Thomas Spurdance, Acts and Monuments. Pag. <hi>2025.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>I receiue Chriſt by faith, by beleeuing in him;</hi> but the bread being receiued is not GOD,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:990:60"/>for, God dwelleth not in Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples made with hands: you doe euill to cauſe the people to kneele downe and worſhip the bread.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi> This may ſerue to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute the Papiſts, who fall into the contrary extreme, and giue ſo much reuerence to it, as that they worſhip, and kneele to it, as to God.<note place="margin">Concil tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den: ſeſſ: <hi>13.</hi> Can. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> They hold, and it was ſo decreed in the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> that the Sacrament ſhould be adored, euen with the higheſt degree of worſhip, <hi>(cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu latriae)</hi> which is proper to God, that it ſhould be carryed about in ſolemne Proceſſions, to be adored of the people; and whoſoeuer held the contrarie, was pronounced accurſed. But this Sacrament is onely to bee reuerenced as an holy myſtery,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:990:60"/>not to be adored with any reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious worſhip. The Apoſtles receiued it at the handes of Chriſt ſitting, not kneeling, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it, not lifting vp their hands to it, &amp; Chriſt bids them <hi>take, eate, drinke, and doe all in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of me,</hi> to teach vs, how vaine, and idle the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Papiſts is, in worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the Sacrament, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſt appointed, nor the Apoſtles acknowledged.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi> This may ſerue to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue thoſe, that neuer looke to their feete, but come raſhly to this Sacrament, without feare, or reuerence: they neuer conſider, that God is there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. It befalleth to many of them, as it befell to <hi>Iacob</hi> while he ſlept; <hi>The Lord was there,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 28.</note> 
               <hi>but he was not aware:</hi> So the Lord
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:990:61"/>is here, but they conſider it not; they ſtand gazing on the reſt of the Communicants, as if they ſhould be asked that que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, when they come home, <hi>What went you out to ſee?</hi> and not what to receiue. But doe theſe men thinke God is preſent? that they ſtand before Angels? ſurely, they know it not, if they did they would not be ſo raſh, and careleſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 3. Here we are taught to demeane our ſelues reuerently, and with feare, while we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to receiue, Conſidering 1. the worth, and price of this Supper, it coſt the ſonne of <hi>God</hi> his precious life, he came downe from his throne of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie; humbled himſelfe: was reputed a baſe ſeruant, and offered himſelfe a ſacrifice to
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:990:61"/>die for vs, that we might liue: 2. The daintie cheare in this Supper, the bodie and bloud of him, who is the ruler of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth: the Lord, at whoſe becke the Angels trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and by whom both quicke and dead ſhall be iudged at the laſt day. 3. The maieſtie of him that ſits at the Table with vs: which is God Almightie, that foldeth the heauens in his ſpan, and before whom heauen and earth ſhall paſſe away like a ſcrole: 4. the perſon that inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs to this feaſt: no meane ſeruant, but a Lord, euen Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">Col. 1.15.</note> the expreſſe Image of his Father. 5. Our owne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe; we deſerue not to eate at this table, hauing beene conceiued in filthineſſe, and wallowing euer ſince, in the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:990:62"/>mire of iniquitie: theſe ſhould make vs feare, and quake, as <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> cryed out at <hi>Bethell,</hi> that is, at the houſe of God. <hi>How feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is the the place?</hi> Surely <hi>it is none other but the houſe of God, and this is the gate of heauen:</hi> So in reſpect, that Chriſt inuiteth vs, giueth himſelfe to be our foode; that God alſo is preſent at this Table, and wee for our parts are moſt vnworthie to fit thereat, or to feede of the meate thereon: we ought to cry out, ſurely, <hi>this is the Lords table,</hi> and all the meate ſet vpon it is of Chriſts prouiſion, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we will eate it with feare and reuerence. If a poore man ſitting at a knights boord trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and feare at euery bit of meat that he puts in his mouth, how much more ſhould wee
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:990:62"/>feare that ſit at this boord, where the Lord of Heauen is preſent. If <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, Euangeliſt, and a Prophet,<note place="margin">Mat. 3.11.</note> thought himſelfe vnworthie to beare Chriſts ſhooes: O Lord how vnworthie are wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane wretches to eate Chriſts fleſh, and to drinke his bloud. If the Woman that had the bloudie iſſue, feared to touch the hemme of Chriſts garment, how ſhould we tremble to eate his fleſh, and to drinke his all-healing bloud? Oh therefore let vs come with pure eyes, and heart, to ſee, and receiue the <hi>Arke of the new Couenant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 1.19.</note> 
               <hi>in whom dwelleth all the fulneſſo of the Godhead bodily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third dutie touching our good behauiour, in the time of receiuing, is, the particular ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:990:63"/>of the Sacrament vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a mans ſelfe, while he is in receiuing of it, and this is done by meditating vpon the holy actions, and rites, which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Chriſts inſtitution are vſed in, and about it: for it hath pleaſed God (conſidering our weakeneſſe) to appoynt thoſe rites as meanes, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to lift vp our mindes to the ſerious contemplation of his heauenly graces.</p>
            <p>We muſt apply this Sacrament 3 wayes, as it is
<list>
                  <item>1. a Supper.</item>
                  <item>2. a Seale.</item>
                  <item>3. a commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. As a ſupper on this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, when the Miniſter ſetteth apart, and conſecrateth by the Word, the bread and wine for Sacramentall ſignes. I am to thinke, how God the Father, of
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:990:63"/>his meere loue hath ſet apart, and conſecrated his ſonne, yea,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.27.</note> (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh) ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him to be my mediator and redeemer: when he breakes the Bread, and powreth the Wine, I muſt meditate, how that Chriſts bodie was broken, and his bloud ſhed for my ſinnes: when he giueth the bread and the wine, I am to thinke, that then God is offering, &amp; giuing me his owne ſonne, to feed me vnto eternall life: When I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the bread, and wine, and feede on them, I muſt meditate of the receiuing of Chriſt, and of my feeding on him by faith, to the cheriſhing, and nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my ſoule: <hi>Except I eate his fleſh and drinke his bloud,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh: 6.51.57.</note> 
               <hi>there is no life in me,</hi> I am but dead, and for this cauſe <hi>did hee come
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:990:64"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:990:64"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:990:65"/>downe from heauen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 2.13.</note> that hee might giue life to me, and to the world of the faithfull.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. As a ſeale: for, as a ſeale ſet to a Deed of gift, confirmeth all things therein promiſed; So when I receiue this Sacrament it ſealeth vp in my heart an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of all Gods promiſes: therefore God is ſayd to haue ſealed vs,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.13 14.</note> and to haue giuen vs the earneſt of his ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Now the promiſes which are ſealed vnto vs, and which faith layeth hold on this Sacrament, reſpect, 1. our Redemption, 2. Reconciliation. 3. Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. 4. Preſeruation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Thoſe that concerne my Redemption, are theſe, &amp; ſuch like,<note place="margin">Tit 2.14. Heb. 4.14.15. 1 Ioh: 3.8.</note> that <hi>Chriſt died for me:</hi> that <hi>he hath redeemed me from ſinne, and Sathan, from hell, from the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:990:65"/>wrath, and curſe of God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal: 3.13. Mat. 1.21.</note> that <hi>hee hath ſaued me from all my ſinnes:</hi> that <hi>they are all forgiuen for his ſake:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>and I am releaſed of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment due vnto them:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.3 4</note> that <hi>hee hath kept the Law for me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled all righteouſneſſe in my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3.24.25. Mat. 17.5. Rom. 4.21.</note> 
               <hi>that his righteouſneſſe is imputed vnto me, and that God accepteth it as mine owne, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe that concerne my Reconciliation, are theſe, and ſuch like, that <hi>Chriſt hath recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled me to God his Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.10.11.</note> 
               <hi>by whom I haue receiued the attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> that he hath purchaſed the fauour,<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.14.</note> and good will of God towardes me: that God is my Father, and I am his child:<note place="margin">Gal. 4.6.7.</note> that he loues me in Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ier. 31.3.</note> and will loue me vnto the end: that he is well pleaſed with mee in his ſonne Chriſt:<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.8.9 10. &amp;c.</note> that he is well
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:990:66"/>pleaſed with my prayers,<note place="margin">1 Ioh: 5.14</note> to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept them; and with all my workes,<note place="margin">Mat. 18.20.</note> and exerciſes to giue me a bleſſing in them, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thoſe which concerne our Sanctification, are theſe, and ſuch like:<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.17 18.19.</note> that I ſhall <hi>receiue the ſpirit of Chriſt,</hi> whereby I ſhall be endued, not onely with knowledge, faith, repentance, the gift of prayer,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.9</note> and all other graces neceſſarie for mee, but alſo that I <hi>ſhall bee ſanctified throughout,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 The. 5.23</note> 
               <hi>both in ſpirit, ſoule, and bodie;</hi> and this will appeare, when my minde ſhall abound with all good motions,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.29.</note> and heauenly meditations,<note place="margin">Epheſ 4.23 24.</note> when my heart ſhall be filled with all righteouſneſſe in Chriſt,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.11.</note> with all good deſires, &amp; holy affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: when my will ſhall be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect,<note place="margin">Luk. 22.42.</note> and obedient to <hi>the will of
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:990:66"/>God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.5</note> when my words ſhall be the words of God <hi>able to edifie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 4.29.</note> 
               <hi>and miniſter grace to the hearers:</hi> when my workes ſhall be ſuch,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.10</note> as becommeth them that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the feare of God: when I <hi>ſhall be a veſſell vnto honour ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.21</note> and meete for my maſters vſe: and when I ſhall ſerue God in loue, and good workes, that the name of our <hi>Lord Ieſus may be glorified in me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 1.11.12.</note> 
               <hi>and I in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Thoſe which concerne my Preſeruation, are theſe, &amp; ſuch like: that I am an <hi>heire of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1.14.</note> 
               <hi>ſealed vp vnto the day of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.17. Epheſ. 4.30</note> ſo that the <hi>Lord will deliuer me from euery euill worke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.18</note> and preſerue me vnto his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which is kept for me and I for it:<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.3.4.5.</note> Hee hath promiſed to ſend his Angels to attend,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.14.</note> and waite vpon me day and night,<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.7.</note>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:990:67"/>to defend, and keepe mee from all dangers,<note place="margin">Pſal. 91.11.12. &amp;c.</note> and to miniſter, and bring to my hand all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for me, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. This Sacrament muſt be applyed as a Communion, for as it is called a ſupper, and a ſeale, ſo a Communion, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that Communion, and fellowſhip the Communicant hath with Chriſt, and his fellow members.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.16.</note> 
               <hi>The Cup of bleſsing which we bleſſe is it not a Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The application is true, and ſound: firſt, when I feele that I am in the preſence of God,<note place="margin">Iſa: 44.10.</note> and that my ſoule hath communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and fellowſhip with <hi>God</hi> the Father,<note place="margin">Zoph: 3 17</note> and with his ſonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ioh: 14.16 23. Ioh: 17.20.</note> as verily as my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die hath communion with bread, and wine: 2. When that
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:990:67"/>I feele I haue fellowſhip and communion with all the Saints of God:<note place="margin">Epheſ 3.7.</note> that I am vnſeparablie knit &amp; ioyned to all my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.17 1 Ioh: 1.7. 1 Cor. 12.13.25. Rom. 12.10 Epheſ. 4 16. Act. 4.32.</note> and brethren by loue, &amp; doe liue in the practiſe of loue, like a liuely, and feeling mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the bodie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 1. This confutes the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, that hold it ſufficient to looke, and gaze on this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Pixe, to worſhip it, but not to apply it: the Laitie are debarred from it, that it might not profit them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 2. Muſt this Sacrament bee particularly applyed, this ſheweth that many receiuing it, receiue little profit by it for want of application; ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue in 1. ignorance: 2. others vnprepared: 3. other ſome for faſhion: 4. others becauſe the
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:990:68"/>ſeaſon ſerueth: 5. others for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of their taſte: 6. o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to feede their bodies; few for the right end and vſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 3. Diſburden thy ſelfe of all worldly thoughts, and vaine cogitations, and let thy ſoule be as emptie of them, as the poore mans cofer is of gold and Iewels: hereby a way is pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to walke in heauenly medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and freedome purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to thinke ſeriouſly vpon this Sacrament.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt dutie tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching our good behauiour in the action of receiuing the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament is, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> that we muſt receiue it with ioy and delight. In the Scripture it is called a <hi>feaſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 19.7.</note> a <hi>banquet;</hi> it is compared to the <hi>Marriage feaſt</hi> of the Kings ſon.<note place="margin">Mat. 22.2.</note> As the gueſts that are called to
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:990:68"/>ſuch feaſts doe much reioyce, ſo muſt we when we come to this heauenly feaſt; like the Children of Iſraell, that obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the <hi>feaſt of vnleauened bread ſeuen dayes with great gladneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chro. 30.21.22.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Our ioy in this banquet ſhould exceed; all other reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings in naturall, or temporall feaſts ſhould ſtoope vnto it. In this is a kingdome; <hi>righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14.17</note> 
               <hi>and ioy in the holy Ghoſt,</hi> in thoſe nothing but bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily ſuſtenance. This ioy will encreaſe, as our aſſurance of Gods mercy towards vs encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. The holy Ghoſt, who is our earneſt penie,<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.13.14.</note> is giuen vnto vs to aſſure vs of the fulfilling of Gods promiſes: ſo that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing receiued him, and feeling him ſtirred vp in vs more and more by this Sacrament,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.12</note> we
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:990:69"/>reioyce vnder the hope of the glorie of God,<note place="margin">2 Co. 5.5.6</note> yea, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſayth, we haue cauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, <hi>with ioy vnſpeakeable, and glorious.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A good ſhew of ioy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe did many of the Iewes then giue, when Chriſt riding into Ieruſalem on an Aſſe, they ſpread their garments in the way, cut downe branches from the trees, and ſtrawed them in the way, and cryed through the ſtreets of Ieruſalem, ſaying; <hi>Hoſanna the ſonne of Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 21.8.9</note> 
               <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be he that commeth in the name of the Lord, Hoſanna thou which art in the higheſt heauens.</hi> Here was great tokens of ioy, and gladneſſe: but how much more gladneſſe ſhould be in vs, ſeeing Chriſt hath not onely vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to come into our ſtreetes,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:990:69"/>but into our houſes, and our hearts. Great ioy was in all <hi>Samaria</hi> when <hi>Philip</hi> came thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to preach among them:<note place="margin">Act. 8.6.8.</note> but greater ſhould our ioy bee, among whom Chriſt inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and to whom he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen his owne fleſh to eate, and his owne bloud to drinke for our ſpirituall, and eternall nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 1. This point may ſerue for direction, to order our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires aright in the matter of ioy. Euery man loues a glad heart; and wiſheth ioy: but therein many miſtake. 1. One reioyceth in his ſubſtance,<note place="margin">Iob 31.25.</note> 
               <hi>he hath gotten much.</hi> 2. Another reioyceth in his <hi>promotion.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Heſt. 5.11.</note> Another doa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vpon that <hi>mad mirth</hi> which <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeakes of. 4.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 2.2.</note> Another reioyceth in a Table richly<note place="margin">Dan. 5.1.2.3. &amp;c.</note>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:990:70"/>deckt, an ouerflowing Cup, a faring deliciouſly euery day. 5. Another reioyceth at the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> of him whom he hates, 6.<note place="margin">Iob 31.29.</note> Another reioyceth in ſinne, and wickedneſſe.<note place="margin">Pro. 10.23.</note> 
               <hi>It is a paſtime to a foole to doe wickedly.</hi> It is the <hi>drunkards</hi> ioy to be at the Cup early,<note place="margin">Iſa. 5.11.</note> and to ſit <hi>till the wine haue enflamed them.</hi> The twi-light glads the heart of the <hi>adulterer.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 24.15.</note> The <hi>oppreſſor</hi> danceth vpon the threſhold of him that is oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.<note place="margin">Zeph. 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>Iſmael</hi> geireth at <hi>Iſaac.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 21.9.</note> Holy <hi>Iob</hi> was as a Tabret to the godleſſe ones;<note place="margin">Iob 17.6.</note> and the <hi>drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards made ſongs on Dauid.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 69.12.</note> Men imagine <hi>ſummum bonum,</hi> their chiefe felicity to conſiſt in their ioyes. But alas, how much are they deceiued; for, what are all theſe ioyes in compariſon of that we treate of. Indeed if it
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:990:70"/>be rightly conſidered, what true comfort can a man take in any thing, ſo long as the dyet of his ſoule is not the ioy of his heart. Howſoeuer the Deuill teacheth men to forget the conſideration hereof, that ſo he may lead them like an Oxe to the ſlaughter, not knowing that they are in danger, yet if euer at any time the conſcience bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened to thinke on this, the very remembrance of it is like the beholding of the hand vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wal to <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> which when he ſaw it, put him quite out of his humour of iollitie; it was not then the delicate taſte of his wine, nor the fatneſſe of his kids, nor the royaltie of his Gueſts, not the fineneſſe of his fare, could keepe his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance from changing, his
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:990:71"/>thoughts from troubling, and his ioynts from beating one vpon another.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 2. This may perſwade vs to affect this ioy, and to prefer it before all contentments: Here we are aſſured that our labour is not in vaine. Thou ſhalt haue ioy in ſeeking for this ioy, it ſhall be gladneſſe to thy ſoule, to heare of this glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: no greater contentment in the world to an hungry beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, then to heare of a good dinner, and to feede therein, Oh then that thou couldſt bee perſwaded to ſeeke this ioy, and in a kinde of diſtaſte of all other Ioyes, which are not worth the naming, to cry out, <hi>Lord euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more giue me this Ioy:</hi> Then the meate in this Supper would be moſt ſweete to thy ſoule, and
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:990:71"/>thy chiefeſt pleaſure.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 3. This may ſerue as a touchſtone to try our ſelues by, whether our ſtomackes bee in good caſe, and whether we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this Sacrament aright, to Gods glorie, and our owne comfort, or no; If we doe, then we reioyce, take pleaſure, and delight in it more then euer we did in any worldly feaſt, or ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet; here is the daintieſt meat, and moſt precious banquet, that euer we came to; Here e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery diſh in this feaſt is made of the moſt precious bodie and bloud of Chriſt, which is able to feede our ſoules, whereas all other banquets can but onely feede our bodies.<note place="margin">Luk. 19.6.</note> As <hi>Zacheus</hi> receiued Chriſt ioyfully when he came to his ſoule, much more into his heart, ſo thoſe
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:990:72"/>that haue ſound ſtomackes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this ſacrament with great ioy and gladneſſe, becauſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Chriſt is come home vnto them, and hath brought ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with him.</p>
            <p>Thus much of the duties touching our good behauiour in the Action of Receiuing.</p>
            <p>The third ſort of duties in our good behauiour after the Receiuing of the Sacrament follow: The duties are foure;</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Thankefulneſſe to God.</item>
               <item>2. Carefulneſſe to grow in grace and ſtrength, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the nouriſhment re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued.</item>
               <item>3. A worthie walking in the ſtrength of this foode recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to Gods glory, and the good of his Church, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>4. A ſpirituall watchfulneſſe,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:990:72"/>by prayers, &amp; ſupplications, with all perſeuerance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, that we may continue in well doing vnto the end, and in the end.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The firſt dutie, which (after our receiuing) we ought to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, is thankfulneſſe to God. We muſt ſhew our ſelues thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to God, for beſtowing ſo heauenly, and bleſſed a feaſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs.<note place="margin">1 The. 5.18</note> 
               <hi>In all things</hi> (ſayth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) <hi>giue thankes.</hi> Now if in all things, in our publique feaſtes, yea, in all our afflictions, and troubles, then much more are we bound to be thankfull for the great benefit of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption beſtowed vpon vs in this heauenly banquet; wherby being ſlaues vnto ſin, drudges vnto Sathan, and ſubiect vnto hell and condemnation, we are
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:990:73"/>deliuered both from ſinne, and Sathan, from hell, &amp; euerlaſting deſtruction. A notable example hereof we ſee in Chriſt, and in his Diſciples, when they had ended this ſupper,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.30.</note> they depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not before they had <hi>ſung a Pſalme of thankeſgiuing</hi> vnto the Lord.<note place="margin">Mar. 14.26</note>
            </p>
            <p>Reaſons to prouoke, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce vs hereunto, (if we haue had any true taſte of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in this Supper) are theſe;</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> 1. Hereby we haue experience of the great goodneſſe of God, &amp; of the loue of Chriſt towards vs, who hath beene content to feede vs with his owne body &amp; bloud: wherby being wounded, and dead with ſinne, we are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liued, and nouriſhed vp vnto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life. We read of the Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican, that for loue to her yong
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:990:73"/>ones being deadly ſtung with ſome venemous ſerpent, ſhee is content to haue her owne breſt pearced, that the bloud might guſh out, to nouriſh, feede, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, and recouer them: So our Pellican Ieſus Chriſt for the loue he bare to vs (being ſtung to death by the venemous Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent Sathan,) was content to haue his bodie pearced and his bloud ſhed to feed, and preſerue vs. Therefore the Apoſtle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering this loue of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him in Chriſt, prayed for the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> that they may know <hi>this loue of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.19 20.21.</note> 
               <hi>which paſſeth knowledge that they might be filled with all the fulnes of God, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> A ſecond Reaſon to moue vs to thankefulneſſe is this: in this Sacrament we receiue the ſeale
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:990:74"/>of all Gods promiſes, and of all the aſſurances of our owne ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. If a pardon ſhould come to a malefactor, he would be a glad, and a thankfull man, but when he ſeeth the Kings broad ſeale put to it, much more ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and thankefull, for then he knoweth all is cockſure, it is no forged Counterfeit: So, the King of heauen and earth, hath not onely giuen vs a pardon, but alſo hath ſet to it his ſeale in this Sacrament, therefore we ſhould alwayes bee ſinging Pſalmes of praiſe, and lift vp our hearts with ioyfull thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe vnto the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> A third Reaſon is. In this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t we feele our ſelues moſt ſtrongly knit vnto Chriſt, and vnto his Church, ſo that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can remoue vs from the
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:990:74"/>loue of Chriſt, and his Saints, and we haue ſuch continuall comfort in the ſenſe &amp; feeling of both, that we haue not onely iuſt cauſe of ioy, but alſo of thankefulneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vſe.</note> This may ſerue to giue a checke to our vnthankfulnes, as for all Gods benefits, ſo eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for the Crowne of all the reſt, euen his Son Chriſt, giuen vnto vs in this Sacrament: this is a bolt, and a barre to keepe Gods benefits from vs, wee will not be thankful for them, when we haue receiued them. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefulneſſe, ſayth one,<note place="margin">Ventus exic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans, et vrens fluenta gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae. Bernar.</note> is a block that ſtops vp the paſſages of Grace: and it turneth the bleſſings of God into curſes: becauſe the <hi>Gentiles were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefull,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.21.22. 2 Tim. 3.2.</note> the Lord infatuated their vnderſtanding: It is a ſin
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:990:75"/>moſt hatefull to man, ſay he is vngratefull,<note place="margin">Ingratum dixeris om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia dixeris. Minus Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianus.</note> and thou mayeſt well ſay, he is euery way faulty. If we reſpect Gods Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that commandeth vs to be thankful in all things, or the practiſe of Chriſt, and his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, that after the receipt of this Sacrament gaue thankes, or the loue of God that ought to mooue vs to thankefulneſſe, or the ſeale of our pardon, which miniſtreth matter of thankefulneſſe, or the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip we haue with Chriſt, and beleeuers, which vrgeth vs to be thankefull, let vs then teſtifie our thankfulneſſe to God with the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 116.12.13</note> ſaying; <hi>What ſhall I render vnto the Lord for all his mercies? I will take the cup of ſaluation, and call vpon the name of the Lord:</hi> the ſacrifice of
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:990:75"/>thankſgiuing is as pleaſant, and acceptable vnto God, as is any ſacrifice, and therefore by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> the Lord ſayth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.23.</note> 
               <hi>Who ſo offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth me thankes and prayſe, he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth me,</hi> euen with moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent honour.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond dutie, after wee haue receiued this ſacrament, is carefulnes to grow in ſtrength, and to encreaſe in ſpirituall grace. We muſt ſtriue to feele encreaſe, and take heed that we be not vnprofitable in our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts: As <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh of the Word, it muſt be deſired, to the end, <hi>we may grow by it:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.2.</note> ſo we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and receiue this ſacrament that we may gather ſtrength, &amp; grow thereby in grace, till at laſt we come to a perfect and a full age in Chriſt. Our Sauiour te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth of himſelfe,<note place="margin">Ioh: 15.1.2.3.</note> that <hi>he is the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:990:76"/>vine, and his father is the huſband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, euery brauch that bringeth not forth fruit in him, he taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 3.</note> 
               <hi>but euery one that bringeth forth fruit he purgeth it that it may bring forth more fruit.</hi> This duty of growing is much vrged in Scripture, <hi>we beſeech you bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and exhort you in the Lord Ieſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.4.10.</note> 
               <hi>that yee increaſe more, and more.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.18. Heb. 6.1.</note> 
               <hi>Grow in grace. Let vs bee led forward vnto perfection, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> compareth the righteous vnto the Sunne,<note place="margin">Pro. 4.18.</note> that <hi>ſhineth more and more vnto the perfect day.</hi> This is a manifeſt truth, neither is there any point plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner then this, that the children of God after grace receiued, muſt alwayes be growing. And the Reaſons of it are theſe;</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> 1. Becauſe otherwiſe we fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the end of the Sacrament,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:990:76"/>which is to feede vs, that wee may gather ſtrength, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of grace.<note place="margin">Pſal. 92.12.13.14.</note> As a poore man comming to a good banquet is much refreſhed, ſtrengthened, and cheared thereby: So the Lord hath appointed this ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet,<note place="margin">Eze. 47.12.</note> that all the good graces of our ſoules begun in vs, which are but poore, and weake, may receiue much ſtrength and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> 2. Becauſe otherwiſe, we in reſpect of our owne good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue Gods graces in vaine, if we thriue not, and proſper not thereby. A thing which the Apoſtle would haue vs eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to looke vnto, exhorting and beſeeching vs in the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Corinthians, to take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eede to our ſelues,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.1.</note> leaſt <hi>we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the grace of God in vaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:990:77"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> 3. If we receiue this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in vaine, the danger of it is great, for, God will one day moſt ſurely puniſh it. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Sauiour Chriſts ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is, that al vnfruitful &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſeruants that would not reape profit by Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and talents, ſhall be caſt into vtter darkneſſe, where is nothing but torments,<note place="margin">Mat 25.26 30.31</note> 
               <hi>weeping, wailing, and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 1. This may ſerue to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue thoſe, that keepe one ſtanding, and one ſtay in their Profeſſion, and Religion, and though they haue had the meanes of grace long, and vſed them often, yet there is no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of grace, no encreaſe of knowledge, faith, repentance, new obedience, &amp;c. They can goe from day to day to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:990:77"/>of the Word, and other godly exerciſes, but ſtill they are at one ſtay, as ignorant, as ſenſeleſſe, as void of true iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of as bad a Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. But alas what a fearefull ſtate, and condition is this. If a childe grow neither in length, nor ſtrength, nor fatneſſe, after many yeares feeding, ſucking, attending on him, &amp;c. ſurely the mother will be out of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite with him. So when the Lord ſhall feed vs in ſeaſonable time, and we ſhall be all at one, ſtand at a ſtay, neither thriuing in knowledge, nor encreaſing in good affection towards reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, he will be out of all good conceits with vs, and at laſt giue vs ouer to our owne ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe. The ſicke perſon that is ſo ſicke that he feeles not his
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:990:78"/>diſeaſe, and wants a ſtomacke, that he cannot eate is much pitied, and lamented, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one ſaith of him, ſurely he cannot liue: So, theſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue Gods graces in vaine, in reſpect of the ſence of comfort in themſelues, though not in vaine in reſpect of God; theſe men, I ſay, that reape no profit by receiuing the Sacrament, are much to be pitied, for they are neare vnto death, and their end will be damnation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 2. This ſerueth alſo for our Inſtruction; Let vs ſtriue af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter perfection, that we may dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grow from perfection to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, till we become perfect men in Chriſt Ieſus. Let vs continually pray with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Lord encreaſe our faith:</hi> and let vs labour by all holy
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:990:78"/>meanes of hearing the Word preached, and reuerent vſe of the bleſſed Sacrament to grow more and more in faith. Let vs pray with the Prophet,<note place="margin">Pſal. 68.28.</note> 
               <hi>Stabliſh the thing, O God that thou haſt wrought in vs.</hi> And let vs la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to be daily more &amp; more grounded, and ſtabliſhed in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery grace that the Lord hath wrought in vs. And if alreadie we doe thus, let vs comfort our ſelues in this, that we doe as we ought, and let vs hold on our good courſe vnto the end.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third dutie after our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of the Sacrament is, that hauing gotten ſtrength, &amp; encreaſe of grace thereby, both in our generall calling, as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, &amp; in the ſpeciall calling, wherein God hath ſet vs, wee muſt walke worthie this badge
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:990:79"/>of our high and honourable profeſſion, whereunto wee are called by glorifying God, and edifying his Church. This dutie is ſet downe in the Epiſtle of <hi>Paul</hi> to the Epheſians, where the Apoſtle exhorteth vs to <hi>walke worthie of</hi> that high,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.1.</note> and honourable <hi>vocation, whereunto we are called.</hi> This made <hi>Paul</hi> goe vnto God in the behalfe of the Theſſalonians, as he ſayth, <hi>We pray alwayes for you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 1.11.12.</note> 
               <hi>that our God would count you worthie of this calling, and fulfill all the good pleaſure of his goodneſſe, and the worke of faith with power, that the name of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt may be glorified in you, and yee in him, according to the grace of God, and our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> As we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue our naturall foode, that we may grow in ſtrength, or at
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:990:79"/>leaſt haue our ſtrength preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that ſo we may be able to vnder-goe our callings; ſo in this Sacrament we receiue our ſpirituall foode, that thereby gathering ſtrength in the inner man, we may be the better able to glorifie God by walking in our callings;<note place="margin">Mat. 5.16.</note> 
               <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine,</hi> ſayth our Sauiour, <hi>that men ſeeing your good workes, may glorifie your Father which is in Heauen:</hi> And the ground of all this ought to be the loue of God in Chriſt: therefore ſayth <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 The. 2.12</note> 
               <hi>I beſeech you that ye would walke worthie of God, who hath called you to his kingdome:</hi> And this we ſhall doe,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> 1. when <hi>wee preſent our bodies a liuing ſacrifice holy, and acceptable to God:</hi> and 2. when for Conſcience ſake we endeuour to keepe Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:990:80"/>
               <hi>If ye loue me,</hi> ſayth Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.15.21.</note> 
               <hi>keepe my Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> For, <hi>he that loueth my Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, &amp; keepeth them is he that loueth me, &amp; he that loueth me, ſhall be loued of my Father, and I will loue him, and will manifeſt my ſelfe to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Reaſons of this point: firſt, we profeſſe our ſelues the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, and true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, it becommeth vs to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt our ſelues ſo in our calling.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, we are called to a kingdome, which makes <hi>Paul</hi> ſtile this Calling,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.14.</note> an <hi>high</hi> or <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernall Calling:</hi> Not ſo much becauſe the Caller is heauenly, but becauſe the honour, to which therby we are aduanced, is indeed heauenly. Hence alſo it is termed,<note place="margin">Heb. 3.1.</note> the <hi>heauenly vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> not ſo much becauſe the
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:990:80"/>author, meanes, and manner, is heauenly, but becauſe the ſtate, whereto we are brought is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly, and glorious.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ob:</note> But how may I diſcerne this worthie walking?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sol.</note> By theſe three ſignes: the firſt is for a man to reſiſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and all his temptations, and neuer to make himſelfe a drudge, and a ſlaue vnto ſinne any more. The Apoſtle exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the Epheſians, to put on the whole armour of God, that <hi>we may be able to ſtand againſt the aſſaults of the Deuill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.11.12.</note> 
               <hi>for we wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle not againſt fleſh, and bloud, but againſt principalities, and powers, againſt the rulers of the darkeneſſe of this world, &amp;c.</hi> What this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Armour, both offenſiue and defenſiue meaneth, is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther expreſſed in that Chapter.<note place="margin">Ver. 14.15.</note>
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:990:81"/>And for ſinne, let not that <hi>haue dominion ouer vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.12.14.</note> 
               <hi>for, we are not vnder the law, but vnder grace:</hi> and wee may very well know, that <hi>to whom we yeeld our ſelues ſeruants to obey,</hi>
               <note place="margin">16.</note> 
               <hi>his ſeruants wee are to whom we obey, whether of ſinne vnto death, or of obedience vnto righteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond, is for a man to liue blameleſſe, and vnſpotted of the world, to auoid offence, and to forſake that which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and not onely ſo,<note place="margin">1 The. 5.22</note> but to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from <hi>all appearance of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.</hi> S. <hi>Peter</hi> exhorteth vs, not only to <hi>abſtaine from fleſhly luſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.11.</note> 
               <hi>which fight againſt our ſoules,</hi> but alſo to liue ſo,<note place="margin">12.</note> that <hi>our conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be honeſt among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> and wicked men, that they perceiuing <hi>our good workes, may be prouoked to glorifie God in the
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:990:81"/>day of their viſitation.</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> in three ſeuerall places of his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Philippians, perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs to liue vnrebukeable. <hi>Onely let your conuerſation be as becommeth the Goſpell of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 1.27.</note> that is, ſo walke, that it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, our life is framed after the doctrine of the Goſpell, and is anſwerable to our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. Againe, <hi>let vs doe all things without murmuring,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.14.15.</note> 
               <hi>and reaſonings, that we may be blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and pure, and the ſonnes of God without rebuke, &amp;c.</hi> And in another place. <hi>Whatſoeuer things are true, honeſt, iuſt, pure, louely,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4.8.9.</note> 
               <hi>of a good report,</hi> and that are well fraughted with vertue, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue prayſe, let vs thinke on them, <hi>and doe them.</hi> In all theſe places wee are exhorted vnto holineſſe of life, &amp; integritie of conuerſation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:990:82"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third, is for a man to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in loue towardes his Chriſtian brethren, &amp; in mercy towards the poore members of Chriſt. Loue of our brethren, is the ſureſt Euidence of our <hi>tranſlation from death to life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ioh: 3.14</note> the Cogniſance of a Diſciple; It is called that fauourable,<note place="margin">Ioh: 13.35.</note> &amp; well-wiſhing affection, of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren one towardes another: the ſpeciall obiect of this loue, are the brethren, vnder that name come all that are <hi>partakers of like precious faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.1.</note> and ſpirit of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption with our ſelues. The load-ſtone of this loue is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood,<note place="margin">Mat. 10 42.</note> 
               <hi>Diſciples are loued</hi> e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nomine, <hi>becauſe they are Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples;</hi> Gods children, becauſe they are Gods childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſtamped with his Image. The manner of this loue, is 1. naturall, and
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:990:82"/>kindly, proceeding from ſelfe inclination, no outward pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocations: 2. Impartiall, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther poore, or rich. 3. Feruent, much water will not quench it. And the fruits of this loue, are 1. ſociall, conuerſing one with another, for mutuall comfort, and edification. 2. A fellow-feeling of miſeries. 3. a ſuccou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of diſtreſſes, and a chearful diſtribution to their preſent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities.<note place="margin">Rom. 12.13</note>
            </p>
            <p>This laſt fruit of loue is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly required after the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of the Sacrament: for, as GOD hath ſhewed his great mercie vnto vs, in beſtowing vpon vs a ſingular, and a rare banquet: <hi>He hath not dealt ſo with euery Nation;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 147.20</note> So ſhould we ſhew mercie vnto our poore brethren, in beſtowing ſome
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:990:83"/>reliefe vpon them according to our abilitie.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1 Cor. 16. 1 Rom. 15.25</hi> Qui copioſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſunt, &amp; volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, pro ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrio quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuo quod vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum eſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribuunt: &amp; quod ita col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligitur, apud praepoſitum deponitur, &amp;c. Iuſtin Martyr A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polog. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> This was practiſed in the Primitiue Churches; Collections, and Loue-feaſtes were made <hi>for the reliefe of the poore Saints,</hi> thoſe of the richer ſort, finding themſelues willing to giue ſomething, did contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute as they thought fit, and that which was giuen and col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected publiquely, the Ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers did ſo diſpoſe of, that poore widdowes, fatherleſſe children, and all ſicke, lame, &amp; impotent perſons found helpe. And as in publique, ſo alſo in priuate, it behoueth vs to yeeld them ſome reliefe, and to ſend vnto them of our ſuperfluity, as in <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> time vpon the Sabboth,<note place="margin">Nehe. 8.10.</note> after the hearing of the Word, &amp;c. the people did eate, and ſent part <hi>vnto them, for
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:990:83"/>whom none was prouided.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 1. This doctrine may ſhew vs, that moſt men, though by name they be called Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, yet walke vnworthie of this high, and honourable cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling whereunto they are called, they goe on in ſinne without Repentance, and do what they can to diſgrace the Lord, and Author of their profeſſion, giu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing iuſt cauſe of offences, both to God, and the world: vnleſſe they reforme their liues, and labour to be <hi>purged from all fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of the fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.1.</note> 
               <hi>and ſpirit,</hi> their end will be fearefull. It will be the eternall deſtruction of their bodies and ſoules. Of theſe prophane <hi>Eſaues,</hi> and fleſhly Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines, <hi>S. Paul</hi> maketh men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſaying;<note place="margin">Phil. 3.18.19.</note> 
               <hi>There be many that walke</hi> (he ſpake paſſionately,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:990:84"/>with teares) <hi>who are the enemies of Ieſus Chriſt, whoſe end is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</hi> Our Sauiour Chriſt ſayth,<note place="margin">Mat. 18.7.</note> 
               <hi>Woe vnto the world becauſe of offences,</hi> yea, <hi>woe be to that man by whom the offence commeth.</hi> Doeſt thou heare this thou that lieſt in ignorance, that giueſt thy ſelfe to drunkenneſſe, to contempt of the Word, and Sacraments, &amp;c. then lay it to thy heart, thy end if thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in this courſe is damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that which thou moſt delighteſt in, ſhalbe thy ſorrow, and thy glorie ſhall be turned into ſhame. It had bin as good for thee to haue had a Milſtone long agoe tyed about thy neck, and thy ſelfe throwne into the bottome of the Sea, then to haue liued to the offence of GOD, and ſcandalized his
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:990:84"/>Church. It is too much that thou thy ſelfe ſhould bee euill ſpoken of: but the holy Goſpel with the profeſſion of it, and the whole companie of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and godly people, by thy meanes to be blaſphemed, is moſt horrible, and cannot bee without the curſe of God. Oh therefore I beſeech, and entreat you in the feare of God,<note place="margin">Sic viuite, vt nemo de vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis male lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mendacio poſsit? Hierot Epiſt. ad Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum de Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tut. Matriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fam.</note> (when wicked men are giuen to ſpeak euill of you) make them eate their words, and ſo liue, that none may ſpeake euill of you, but that all the world may ſee they lie. Remember <hi>God hath called you not to vncleanneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>but vnto holineſſe;</hi> euery thing in his Calling ſauoureth of holineſſe,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.9.</note> the Calling is holy,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.15.</note> the Caller is holy, the meanes and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is holy,<note place="margin">Ioh: 17.17</note> &amp; the immediate
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:990:85"/>worker, which is the Spirit, is the <hi>fountaine of all holineſſe.</hi> Oh then walke worthie of this cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 2. This may ſhew vs, if we trie our ſelues by the former ſignes, whether we walke wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of our Calling, and liue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our profeſſion, the badge and cogniſance whereof we haue alreadie receiued. If we reſiſt ſin, and Sathan, and ſuffer neither of them to raigne in, nor ouer vs: if we take heed that we be not ſpotted of this preſent euill world: if we loue our brethren, and the members of Chriſt, and with chearfulnes helpe them in their preſent exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents: then we haue receiued grace, by vertue of this heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Manna, and walke in our Callings, to Gods glorie, and
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:990:85"/>the edifying of his Church. But on the other ſide, if we nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſiſt Sathan, nor ſinne, but giue them houſe-roome, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitation, if we cannot in any ſenſe commiſerate, and helpe the neceſſities of our brethren, then we haue but the name of the Calling of Chriſtianitie, Chriſtians indeed wee are not, and deſeruedly, may grieous imputations be caſt vpon vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 3. Seeing after the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of the Sacrament, the workes of mercie are to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, and the wants of the poore relieued: iuſtly may they bee blamed, that depart the Congregation, &amp; giue nothing to the poore, <hi>whoſe bowels ſound like Shaulmes for want of foode, and whoſe faces gather blackneſſe through famine,</hi> We haue thoſe
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:990:86"/>that receiue the Sacrament, and yet ſo miſerable, and ſo voyd of the bowels of compaſſion, that they can ſuffer the pitifull child halfe ſtarued, and hanging vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their mothers breaſt, to crie out, ready to giue vp the ghoſt, <hi>Where is bread, and where is drinke?</hi> And the hearts of the parents to fall aſunder like drops of water, becauſe they haue not to giue vnto them, I would wiſh theſe to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Parable of the rich Glutton, and poore <hi>Lazarus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lak. 16.</note> and the manner of the laſt Iudgement,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> where the wicked are reproued, not for murder, or whoredome, though they ſhall be damned for theſe, but for vnmercifulneſſe, being fed themſelues, they would not giue any foode to the needie.
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:990:86"/>
               <hi>There is no loue of God in ſuch.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ioh: 3.17</note>
            </p>
            <p>Some are ſo eager in ſcraping for their heires, that the poore can get nothing; but that ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is beſt laid vp, which is layd vp in Chriſts <hi>almes boxe,</hi> which is the poore mans hand, for he and his, ſhall finde the benefite of it afterwards. Some in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Almes,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 25.10.11.</note> haue <hi>Nabals</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, they <hi>haue families of their owne, ſhould they take and giue to others?</hi> Some ſtand vpon their termes, they will giue, but with? to wicked men? Yes, to them in great, and extreame neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; ſome indeed to ſpare their purſes, will pretend, either that the perſons be wicked, or that they know them not to bee good. But mans nature is to be pitied, euen in an euill man, &amp; he which giues to a ſinner, not
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:990:87"/>becauſe he is a ſinner,<note place="margin">Non peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, ſed iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumpaupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens nutrit, quia millo non culpam, ſed naturam diligit, &amp;c. Grego: mag.</note> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is a man, relieueth not a ſinfull, but a righteous poore man, becauſe hee reſpects not his fault, but his nature. Mercy vſeth not to iudge of deſerts, but to helpe neceſſitie.</p>
            <p>Some would giue, but they plead their owne pouertie. What thou wanteſt in purſe, beſtow in prayers to God for them, in admonition, inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, conſolation, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>Some will giue ſo far as may ſtand with reputation. What if Chriſt had beene ſo ſtreight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in his bowells to vs-ward, where had our poore ſoules beene? He had honor and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, yet for our ſakes he emptied himſelfe, and became of no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation: and ſhall wee ſtand with his poore members on
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:990:87"/>tearmes of reputation.</p>
            <p>Some giue grudgingly, who when the pennie is out of the purſe, wiſh it in againe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of their liberalitie; theſe are men <hi>with euill eyes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 23.6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And many others will not giue any thing, without much vrging; theſe are like Spunges, they ſucke vp water apace, but they will not let fall a drop, though they be full, till they be ſqueezed.</p>
            <p>I could wiſh that theſe excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes might be ſpared, and poore hungrie ſoules better remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred. Giue vnto them to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie their wants, &amp; giue chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and often, when by anie meanes you heare of their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe. A mercifull man will not ſtay till poore men ſeeke vp him, but he will ſeeke vp the
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:990:88"/>poore, that he may finde them whom modeſtie, and ſhame faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe cauſeth to lie hid, and to conceale their needfull caſes. Oh ſpare ſome diſh from your tables, ſome morſels from your mouths, ſome mony from your treaſurie to relieue them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God commands it, and giueth to you, that you may giue to them. 2. Reckoneth it as done to himſelfe: 3. It com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends your profeſſion, nay, our profeſſion of Chriſtianitie bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs to giue. 4. Thy gift is <hi>depoſitum pietatis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. in Apolog.</note> the ſtocke of godlineſſe: 5. It is pleaſing to God:<note place="margin">Heb. 13.16.</note> it is called a ſacrifice. 6. It is beneficiall to thy ſelfe, God ſuffereth many to labour vnder great miſeries, that hee might crowne the miſerable for their patience, and the mercifull for
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:990:88"/>their beneuolence. 7. Manie promiſes are made to giuers:<note place="margin">Pro. 11.25. Luk. 6.38.</note> Giuing is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, or Communication: If thou giueſt a penie, the poore man giues thee a good prayer, and bleſſeth thee in the name of God,<note place="margin">Iob 29.13. And 31.20.</note> of which <hi>Iob</hi> made great reckoning. Giuing is like to Tennis-play, for, as the Ball that is ſerued, is returned forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly vpon him that ſerued it; So doth God double vpon vs the good that we haue done to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as <hi>Dauias</hi> Prayers <hi>retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into his owne boſome;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 35.13.</note> ſo doe our Almes.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt dutie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired at our hands, after the receiuing of the Sacrament, is, a ſpirituall watchfulnes by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and ſupplications in the ſpirit, both for our ſelues, and
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:990:89"/>the whole Church, with all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance thereunto, that both it, and we may continue in well-doing vnto the end, and in the end.</p>
            <p>This Dutie is ſet forth vnto vs, in the Philippians, where the Apoſtle bids vs be in <hi>nothing carefull,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>but in euery thing by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and ſupplication, together with giuing of thankes, let our requeſt be made knowne vnto God.</hi> And our Sauiour,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.41.</note> bids <hi>vs watch and pray, leaſt we enter into temptation,</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vs to vnderſtand, that it is an eaſie matter to fal from God, and flie to the enemies of our ſaluation, vnleſſe wee make heartie prayers to God for our eſtabliſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> prayed vnto God in the behalfe of the Philippians,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.5.</note> that they might ſtand ſtrong <hi>in their
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:990:89"/>fellowſhip in the Goſpell, from the firſt, to the laſt day;</hi> and ſurely much more needfull is it for vs to pray for conſtancie in good things: ſoone may we fall or ſlip, let vs then pray the more ſeruently, let vs not giue our ſelues any reſt, but ſtill pray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord for our continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> 1. Becauſe of our ſelues, we are able to doe nothing, not to thinke one good thought, ſo, much leſſe performe one good action. It is God that giueth <hi>vs both the will, and the deede;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.13.</note> as Chriſt ſayth,<note place="margin">Ioh: 15.5.</note> 
               <hi>without him we can doe nothing:</hi> therefore it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, that our ſoules ſhould be powred out, and our ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations tendered, that God may be pleaſed, to beginne good things in vs, &amp; then according
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:990:90"/>to his good pleaſure to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue them in vs, and vs in them.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> 2. Becauſe ſleepineſſe in good actions begun, bewraieth our careleſneſſe, cauſeth God to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue,<note place="margin">Reu. 2.5.</note> and to take his ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces away from amongſt vs, and to tranſlate them to another people,<note place="margin">Mat. 21.43.</note> which ſhall bring forth the fruits thereof, to leaue vs to our ſelues, to come againſt vs with wrath, and to bring on vs that ſhamefull Prouerbe, <hi>Loe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.22.</note> 
               <hi>with the dogge they haue turned to their vomit, and with the ſow to the mire.</hi> What greater ſhame then after our eſcape from the filthineſſe of the world, our taſte of the good foode of our ſoules, and of the ioies to come, to turne from the holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement: what a ſhame is it for vs to begin in the ſpirit, and
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:990:90"/>to end in the fleſh, to feede of Angels bread, and then to luſt after the Garlicke, and Onions of Egypt. Great neede it is for vs to caſt down our ſelues in all lowlineſſe, before the throne of Gods maieſtie, and earneſtly begge at his hands, ſtrength, &amp; courage in all good things, and perſeuerance therein, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that if the vncleane ſpirit come for re-entrie, and get poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion,<note place="margin">Luk. 11.24. &amp;c.</note> he will come with ſeuen other vncleane ſpirits, and our laſt end will be the worſt.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> 3. Becavſe wee can neither receiue any grace, nor vſe any good gift well, nor keepe any good thing, nor encreaſe it without watchfulnes by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. <hi>If ye abide in me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh: 15.7.</note> 
               <hi>and my Word abide in you, aske what you will, and it ſhall be done vnto you.</hi> To
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:990:91"/>pray alwayes,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.12 1 The. 5.17 Luk. 18.1.</note> and not to faint, or giue ouer, is a thing much commanded by the holy <hi>Ghoſt.</hi> And as thus we are to watch by prayer, ſo alwayes in our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, this is to be remembred, that we pray, that the Lord his way may be knowne vpon earth, and his ſauing health a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all Nations; that the word of the Lord may haue free paſſage; and that we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue grounded, and ſtabliſhed in the faith, as we haue beene taught in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 1. This may confute the Papiſts, touching their free-wil, ſeeing a man cannot perſeuere, nor do any good thing without Gods ſpeciall aſſiſtance. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer therefore ſhall tell you, that wee haue power in our ſelues, to will, and to doe that
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:990:91"/>which is good, and that wee need onely to be holpen, but not wholy aſſiſted by grace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue him not. <hi>Adam</hi> before his fall had free will to chooſe the good, and to refuſe the euill: but by his fal he loſt that which in his Creation hee had, euen all free-will vnto all things of the ſpirit: ſo that till ſuch time as he be regenerate by the ſpirit of God, he cannot at all by his own power vnderſtand, thinke, will, or doe any thing that is good, but is wholy carryed to that which is euill, and can doe nothing elſe but ſinne.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.14</note> 
               <hi>The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man</hi> (ſayth the Apoſtle) <hi>perceiueth not the things of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God; for, they are fooliſhnes vnto him, neither can he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned:</hi> Where the Apoſtle
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:990:92"/>plainly ſheweth, that the vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate man hath none vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding at all in the wayes of God, and the things that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto his peace, neither can haue till the Lord ſanctifie him by his holy ſpirit, chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his corrupt will, &amp; working in him both the will, and the deed, of his owne good will.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi> This may teach vs, that it is not ſufficient to begin wel, vnleſſe withall we continue in well doing vnto the end, and in the end. The ſecond ſort of euill hearers beganne well,<note place="margin">Mat. 13.</note> but they mard all in that they did not continue; for, (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all their good begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings) in the time of temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they went away. The fiue fooliſh Virgins had flouriſhing Lampes for a while, yet they
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:990:92"/>went out before the comming of the Bridegroome, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were excluded out of his chamber. <hi>Lots</hi> wiſe made great haſt out of <hi>Sodome</hi> for a ſeaſon, but on a ſudden ſhee looked backe, and ſtood ſtill. The <hi>Scribe</hi> that anſwered <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſo promptly, and aptly,<note place="margin">Mar. 12.34</note> out of the Law, was <hi>not farre from the kingdome of God;</hi> yet becauſe he held not on he could not enter. So it is to be feared, that in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of vs there is proneneſſe to retire, and giue out, wee ſtart <hi>aſide like a broken bow.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 78.57.</note> It is a kinde of <hi>wearineſſe</hi> vnto vs,<note place="margin">Mal. 1.13.</note> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a weeke, or a moneth, or a yeare to hold on. I haue known ſome exceeding hote, running ſwift at firſt like <hi>Hazael,</hi> but on a ſudden they became cold,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 2.23</note> and lazie, and grew to a loathing of
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:990:93"/>that which they at firſt extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loued. Looke to it thou which art guiltie to thy ſelfe of thine owne back ſliding. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>Lots</hi> wife, hauing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to forſake the corruptions that are in the world through luſt, continue in the grace of God, and grow forward from grace to grace, til thou be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect man in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>It muſt not be in Religion as in banquets; In the beginning good Wine, and then after that which is worſe, but rather with the Church of <hi>Thyatira,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 2.19.</note> Our <hi>workes muſt be more at laſt then at firſt.</hi> Oh let vs all be carryed forward to perfection,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.12.14.</note> 
               <hi>leauing that which is behind, endeuouring to that which is before, if by any meanes we may attaine the marke,</hi> With the Spouſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.11.</note> 
               <hi>Let vs forget
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:990:93" rendition="simple:additions"/>our owne people, and our Fathers houſe,</hi> that is, the fooliſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation receiued from the Tradition of our Fathers.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Let vs ſo runne that we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine;</hi> For,<note place="margin">Mar. 10.22.</note> 
               <hi>He that goeth forward to the end ſhall be ſaued.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
